<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true relation of the severall negotiations which have pass'd between his Majesty the King of Svveden and His Highness the Elector of Brandenburgh. Translated out of French.</title>
            <title>True relation of the several negotiations which have passed between his Majesty the King of Sweden. English</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3045</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232949</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99898084</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99898084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">133421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 133421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2557:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true relation of the severall negotiations which have pass'd between his Majesty the King of Svveden and His Highness the Elector of Brandenburgh. Translated out of French.</title>
                  <title>True relation of the several negotiations which have passed between his Majesty the King of Sweden. English</title>
                  <author>Charles X Gustav, King of Sweden, 1622-1660.</author>
                  <author>Friedrich Wilhelm, Elector of Brandenburg, 1620-1688.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed and dated at end: Dated from Collen on the Spree, the 14th of Aug. 1658. O. Barron of Suerin, D. Weiman,.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prussia (Germany) --  Foreign relations.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  Foreign relations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:133421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TRUE RELATION OF THE Severall Negotiations which have paſs'd between his Majeſty the King of <hi>SVVEDEN,</hi> AND His Highneſs the Elector of <hi>BRANDENB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RGH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of French.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:133421:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:133421:2"/>
            <head>A TRUE RELATION OF SUCH Paſſages as hapned in the Iourney Undertaken by the Baron of <hi>SUERIN,</hi> and the Honourable M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>WEYMAN, Deputies</hi> on the behalf of the <hi>Prince Elector</hi> of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg</hi> to the <hi>King of Sweden.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">In the Moneths of <hi>May</hi> and <hi>June</hi> 1658.</head>
            <p>IT is not without a great deal of <hi>regret,</hi> that we are <hi>enforced</hi> to begin this Relation by complaints, againſt thoſe who are the cauſes of the deſolation of our beloved and dear Countrey: But its the very laſt extremity which exacts them at our hands, and which obligeth us to make a ſad refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on the pitifull eſtate wherein we have ſeen <hi>Germany</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged, by the Forces of thoſe, who, <hi>under the cloak of Liberty and Religion,</hi> have in ſuch a lamentable manner extenuated that <hi>fair body,</hi> as they have left it but a bare <hi>skeleton:</hi> there is not ſo deſpicable a <hi>German,</hi> who hath but one ſole drop of bloud left in his veins, that cannot be ſenſible hereof, and who can ceaſe from ſighing, at the reherſall of the calamities wherewithall his Countrey hath been afflicted. <hi>We have dearly bought our Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, at the expence of our Eſtates, our Goods, our Bloud, our Honour, and our reputations; and we have forgot what we once our ſelves were, to eſtabliſh the Names of thoſe, who were ſcarce ever heard of, leſs known in the Empire. Nor have they onely ſetled the Seats of their Dominion on our Frontiers, but even our faireſt and moſt beautifull Provinces along the Elve, the Weſer, and the Oder, do groan under the intollerable captivity of their Government; Strangers do triumph over our Liberties,</hi> and they make a mockingſtock of Religion, whileſt under the pretence thereof, they have poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:133421:3"/>of all <hi>Pomerania,</hi> and thoſe other great Eſtates and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories which they enjoy in the reſt of the <hi>Empire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeemed that at length God would have pity on us, and that by <hi>the Peace of Munſter</hi> he would in ſome manner disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burden us of our miſeries; wherfore all men did generally return their thanks and acknowledgments to the Almighty thereon, ſince all men beleeved they might have enjoyed their own in peace, and might have reaped the fruit of their labours in quiet, under their own vines and figg-trees; and thoſe who had overwatched and outlaboured themſelves during the laſt commotions and diſorders, hoped now to carry their hoary heads in peace to their graves.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Swediſh Seepter</hi> was no ſooner departed the hands of a Woman, whenas it became <hi>a burning torch</hi> in the hands of her Succeſſor, to kindle again the wars in <hi>Germany;</hi> the firſt ſparkles whereof appeared in the Swediſh Forces before <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and the full flames not long after burſt out throughout all <hi>Poland,</hi> that famous Kingdom, which ſo often, and ſo glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly ſtood in ſtead of a bulwark and defence to all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; being on all ſides at once ſet upon by an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſtrangers, craved the aid and aſſiſtance of all the world; whenas, <hi>this preſent King of Sweden,</hi> took his time to fall upon its back, whilſt it was involved in a warre with all thoſe other <hi>Barbarians;</hi> and entring it, <hi>by the way of its Proteſtant Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> did menace it with no leſs then <hi>a totall deſtruction;</hi> which it eſcaped by a meer miracle: for as all the world muſt needs know, had not the Almighty put to his helping hand, we had not ſeen it in the condition it is in at this day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Elector all Highneſs of Brandenburg,</hi> having born the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt brunt of theſe diſaſters, foreſeeing that this fire was like to conſume the beſt part of Chriſtendom, uſed his poſſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours <hi>to ſtifle it in the embers;</hi> and after it had blazed forth, <hi>by his earneſt and frequent beſeeching the King of Sweden,</hi> to reflect on the conſequences of this buſineſs, and the abominable ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall which would be given to all the world, <hi>by ſo unjuſt an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion,</hi> and even moved him to give ear to a reaſonable and advantagious Peace: but inſtead of gaining upon the <hi>ſaid Kings minde,</hi> his <hi>Electorall Highneſs</hi> found himſelf neceſſitated to leavy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:133421:3"/>Forces, as well for the defence of his own Territories, which were aſſaulted by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> as to comply with that obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he ſtood engaged in, unto <hi>the Crown of Poland.</hi> True it is, that the ſucceſs was not anſwerable to his expectations, nor to the juſtice of his Forces; but an extream neceſſity, and an overpowring Force, conſtrained his Highneſs <hi>to treat with the</hi> Swedes, <hi>and to agree with them in ſuch a manner as they themſelves would; and tht fatall misfortune of Poland,</hi> brought a generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution on the whole Kingdom, in which it ſeemed, that all the ſeverall Eſtates and Orders thereof, generally, and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly conſpired, to the ruin of that Crown.</p>
            <p>Now, <hi>his Electorall Highneſs wanting the Power of a Protector in chief, neceſſity</hi> did in ſome manner diſpence with him in the duty of a vaſſall; ſo that his waring againſt <hi>Poland,</hi> may be in ſome way excuſed, by the enforced neceſſity which plunged him therein: however, both <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> do full well know, that amidſt the greateſt ſucceſſes of the Swediſh Armies, and even during thoſe Triumphs, in which his <hi>Electorall High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> might juſtly claim ſo great a part, he had alwayes a heart bent to Peace, and continually embraced the Propoſals thereof with joy.</p>
            <p>Inſomuch that the Polonian affairs, meeting with ſuch a change, by reaſon of the Denmark Warre, the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> was forced to quit <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and in a manner, to relinquiſh and renounce thoſe Treaties which he made with his <hi>Electorall Highneſs,</hi> whom the King himſelf counſelled, <hi>to heed his own affairs, and to prevent thoſe diſaſters which threatned the Ducall Pruſſia, by the beſt means he could.</hi> And accordingly by his ſaid Majeſties counſell, his Electorall Highneſs, took his reſolution on the preſent conjuncture of affairs, and did again <hi>reconc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le himſelf to the Crown of Poland;</hi> with this Proviſo however, <hi>That both Parties ſhould chiefly minde the Peace with Sweden;</hi> and that in caſe either, or both were ſo unfortunate as not to bring their good intentions to a deſired effect, as then, his <hi>Electorall Highneſs</hi> ſhould remain in a full and entire liberty, <hi>to act in the Empire, in relation to his own Intereſt, and in conformity to the Peace of Munſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And immediately, notice was given hereof to the <hi>King of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:133421:4"/>Sweden,</hi> and it was repreſented unto him, That by reaſon of the complying with the ſaid Treaty, his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe</hi> could not any longer give the Swediſh Troopes paſſage through his Territories; nor permit that any prohibited Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſes ſhould be unloaden in his Ports. And his Majeſty was at the ſame time requeſted to think upon the <hi>Peace with Poland,</hi> aſſuring him that it might be obtained on very advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious Termes for the <hi>Swedes:</hi> Whereupon the ſaid King declared unto his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> That he was very much inclined thereunto; aſſured the States of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Saxony,</hi> who were aſſembled at <hi>Liepſig, That he would no more march through the Empire into Poland,</hi> and told <hi>Mounſier de Lombres</hi> (the French Ambaſſadour, who alwaies moſt vigorouſly ſeconded the King his Maſters good intentions, towards the procuring of a Peace betwixt the two Crownes) That he would not only reſtore <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> by reimburſing it in a manner for the charges of the War, but that alſo he would immediately nominate his Plenipotentiaires to Treat on the Peace with <hi>Poland:</hi> All which Declarations, gave great hopes for a Peace in the North.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>the King and Crown of Poland,</hi> conſidering that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> would obtain a great advantage from ſuch a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the above-ſaid purpoſe, by <hi>the jealouſie which the</hi> Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites would <hi>harbour thereon,</hi> and by the juſt cauſe which the other Allyes would have to complain of ſuch a particular Treaty; they thought it not fitting to engage themſelves in ſuch like Negotiations, the event whereof was very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and would ruine them, in the opinion of all their Friends. And indeed, they perceived that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> would not explain himſelf, as to the ſumme which he demanded for recompence of <hi>Pruſſia.</hi> And finally, That ſince his ſucceſſes in <hi>Denmark,</hi> he required ſo immenſe a ſumme, as was altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unpoſſible for the Crown of <hi>Poland</hi> to procure, or pay.</p>
            <p>Moreover, his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> perceiving that the State of Affairs in <hi>Denmark,</hi> had changed all the King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s reſolutions, and that he had proceeded to open threats againſt the ſaid <hi>Elector;</hi> he found himſelf obliged, to his great grief, to prepare againſt his violence, whileſt he uſed all the poſſible
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:133421:4"/>and imaginable good Offices toward the advancing and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting of the Peace between the two Crowns: And the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture into which the ſaid <hi>Elector</hi> hath put himſelf, as well by thoſe Alliances which he hath made with his Neighbouring Princes, as by the care which he hath taken to preſerve his Army, and to put his places in defence, did not at all hinder him, to apply his thoughts to deviſe a meanes to beget a Peace between <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sweden;</hi> with a reſolution however, That in caſe he met with too great difficulties therein, at leaſt to hinder the Swediſh Forces from marching through the Territories of the Empire, and getting that way into <hi>Poland,</hi> thereby to prevent the ruine of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pper-Saxony Cerele;</hi> and thoſe iconveniencies which the Swedes would cauſe him to ſuffer, to the prejudice of their verball aſſurances of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, given at the Aſſembly at <hi>Leipſig,</hi> and at the Dyet at <hi>Franckford,</hi> of their good and reall intentions: And ilke man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by this meanes, to <hi>endeavour to ſave and preſerve all</hi> Germany <hi>from the devaſtations by Fire and Sword, wherewithall the King of</hi> Sweden <hi>had threatned it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon, his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> by his Letters of the 10th of <hi>March</hi> of this preſent year (annexed and marked,
<note n="a" place="margin">Proof 1.</note>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted his ſaid Majeſtty to evidence his good intentions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Peace with <hi>Poland,</hi> and to let him ſee the effects of the Promiſe which he made unto him thereon; the ſaid King anſwered him on the 10th of <hi>April</hi> next enſuing (annexed
<note n="b" place="margin">Proof 2.</note>) and told him, That he had long ſince named his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners for the ſaid Treaty of Peace, but that the <hi>Polander</hi> witneſſed ſo ſmall an inclination thereunto; as that he durſt not any longer promiſe himſelf any ſuch thing.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the <hi>Earl</hi> of <hi>Slippenbach,</hi> having at the ſame time invited the <hi>Baron</hi> of <hi>Suerin</hi> (his Electoral Highneſſe of <hi>Brandenburghs,</hi> chief Miniſter of State) to give him a meeting at <hi>Prentſlou,</hi> in the <hi>Marck of Brandenburgh;</hi> he there ſhewed him a <hi>project or draft of an alliance which the King of</hi> Sweden, <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he would make with the King of</hi> Denmark, <hi>and with ſome other Princes and States of Europe;</hi> and preſſed him, on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the King his Maſter, to move his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe</hi> to ſend his Ambaſſadours thereon, unto his Majeſty, and the ſaid
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:133421:5"/>Count, continuing his earneſt preſſing of the ſame, by his Letters of the firſt of <hi>May</hi> (annexed and marked
<note n="c" place="margin">Proof 3.</note>) his ſaid <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoral Highneſſe,</hi> who was the rather induced to incline unto a Peace, by how much he knew that the preſervation of his own Eſtates and Territories did partly depend thereon; gave ear unto the counſel which was given him by the publick Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of <hi>France,</hi> &amp; <hi>England,</hi> and alſo by his Neighbouring Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; by his neareſt Allyes and Kindred, the <hi>Dukes</hi> of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick,</hi> and <hi>Lunenburgh,</hi> and the <hi>Landtgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe;</hi> and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated for this <hi>Embaſſy, the Baron of Suerin,</hi> and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Mr. <hi>Weyman,</hi> one of his <hi>Privy Counſellors of State:</hi> which Ambaſſadours departed from <hi>Berlin</hi> on the 13th day of the Moneth of <hi>May</hi> laſt paſt, and being arrived at <hi>Kiel,</hi> they were very well received in that place, <hi>the Prince of</hi> Sulsbach, <hi>and the Earl of</hi> Slippenbach, coming thither to complement them on the behalf of the <hi>King,</hi> treated them, end entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with a great deal of civility; and in that place, they heard the King was at <hi>Flensbourg:</hi> So that being arrived at <hi>Gottorp</hi> (where they had order to <hi>negotiate</hi> ſeveral things with <hi>that Duke,</hi> being a <hi>Prince of the Empire</hi>) they gave notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the King, who having ſent them word by the <hi>Count Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latin of Sultsbach,</hi> That it was his deſire they ſhould come to <hi>Flensbourg.</hi> they immediately repaired thither.</p>
            <p>At their arrival, they were lodged by the Kings order, and as ſoon as they had ſent their Letters of Credence unto the Court, a Perſon of quality came to complement them on the Kings behalf; which good beginnings, cauſed as great joy in all thoſe who deſired paſſionately the ſetling of a Peace, as the Ambaſſadours themſelves, who flattered themſelves, but with over-ſlender hopes, which vaniſhed in a moment after: <hi>They demanded audience, but they were put off, and delayed by ſeveral pretentions, whileſt divers perſons were imployed to penetrate into the ſecret of their Inſtructions. And the</hi> Swedes <hi>would needs know, whether they were ordered to mention a Peace with</hi> Poland, <hi>and the reſtitution of</hi> Pruſſia; <hi>and they were given to underſtand, That it being unlikely his Majesty could not hear ſuch Propoſitions with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being diſpleaſed, might make a difficulty to give them audience, which they demanded, becauſe it would tend only to exasperate the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:133421:5"/>mindes of both Parties. But that in caſe the ſaid Ambaſſadours had the leaſt power to treat on a particular agreement, and to renew the former Amity between his Majeſty and his Electoral Highneſs, To renounce and forego, the alliance which he had made with</hi> Poland <hi>and the other Confederates, and to promiſe that his ſaid Highneſs would joyn his Forces to the Swedes, thereby to conſtrain their common Enemies to make a Peace, as then his Majeſty would receive the ſaid Ambaſſadours, and hear them with joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which unacuſtomed and irregular way of proceeding, did ſo much ſurprize the ſaid Ambaſſadours, as that they could not chooſe but complain thereof; and did declare, That they could not be admitted unto audience, becauſe it was known that they had, order to motion a Peace, as if that Sacred and Pious name of <hi>Peace,</hi> ought to have been accounted as an abomination, and ad horror; and muſt needs render thoſe odious, who interpoſed therein. However, they profeſſed that there ſhould not be any thing in their Propoſals which might diſpleaſe the King, but that they deſired to be excuſed, if before their being admitted to audience, they diſcovered not their Embaſſy any further: Notwithſtanding, inſtead of advancing their audience, they ſoon diſcovered that the ſaid Embaſſy was not acceptable; and that the King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> becauſe he could not expect or hope to engage his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoral Highneſſe</hi> in a particular Treaty; made uſe of all the meanes he poſſibly could, to ſave himſelf from the reproach which might be caſt upon him; That he would not give ear to the Propoſals of a Peace.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe, they only endeavoured to prolong the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to elude the good intentions of his <hi>Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and publiquely began to laugh at, and deride the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy, begetting daily new difficulties, and alledging that it would be requiſite to <hi>nominate Commiſſioners,</hi> who ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter upon a conference with his <hi>Electoral Highneſs Ambaſſadours,</hi> in the preſence of the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſes</hi> Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours, before they were admitted to an audience by the King; To propound unto them, and to know ſeveral things of them, before which, they could not enter upon any Treaty with them; which was only done a purpoſe, indirectly to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:133421:6"/>diſmiſſe the ſaid Ambaſſadours, by ſo unjuſt a Propoſal; or in caſe they ſhould have been ſo weak as to have condeſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſuch a Conference, of that nature, and to have acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged ſo unlawfull a power; To have obtained thoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages thereby, which they might have hoped from thoſe Tales and Stories which they would have divulged throughout the whole world, to the prejudice of the repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and intereſt of his Electoral Highneſſe.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Swedes</hi> did apparently the rather deſire the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervention of the <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſian Ambaſſadours,</hi> at this pretended conference, that they might thence gain this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to <hi>embroile</hi> his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> with thoſe ſaid Princes; in caſe their Deputies and Commiſſioners ſhould not be ſatisfied with the ſaid Ambaſſadours proceedings, or that they themſelves might take a pretence and occaſion to break with them, in caſe their Teſtimonies ſhould condemn the King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s Proceedings. The Lords <hi>Mevius, Kley</hi> and <hi>Erenſtein,</hi> who were nominated Commiſſioners in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> for the ſaid conference, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly ſignified the Kings reſolution unto the ſaid Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, on the 22th of <hi>June.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto the ſaid Ambaſſadours made Anſwer, and alledged, That they were very much ſurprized at the advice they had received, not believing that in the preſent conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of affairs; when as they might have hoped and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed themſelves an audience from the King, ſuch a Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition could be made unto them: wherefore they deſired time to reſolve upon a definitive Anſwer thereon, and the which they would ſend to the Lord <hi>Mevius.</hi> But before they took their ſaid Reſolution what to anſwer, they viſited the <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſian Ambaſſadours,</hi> who were as much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized as themſelves, and could not imagine nor compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, why the <hi>Swedes</hi> would oblige them to be preſent at a conference, <hi>at which they neither would nor could intervene,</hi> either as <hi>Judges, Parties,</hi> or <hi>Witneſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſomuch that the ſaid Ambaſſadours ſent back word in writing, to the Lord <hi>Mevius</hi> (marked and annexed
<note n="d" place="margin">Proof 4.</note>) That their Inſtructions, commanding them in expreſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:133421:6"/>termes, to addreſs themſelves unto the King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s own Perſon, to demand audience of him; and that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of a conference before the audience, being an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and unuſual a thing, they could not in any wiſe aſſent thereunto: whereon they deſired him to excuſe them to the King, and to obtain from his Majeſty that audience which they had ſo often and ſo earneſtly deſired.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Commiſſioners made anſwer to the foregoing Note, in ſomewhat brisk termes (annexed and marked
<note n="e" place="margin">Proof 5.</note>). That his Majeſty having deemed it neceſſary, in reference to the advice he had received of the ſaid <hi>Electoral Highneſſe</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagements with his Enemies, to cauſe certain Propoſitions to be made unto them; that the Ambaſſadours might diſpoſe themſelves to hear them, if they pleaſed, as well as the other Orders which they had received from his Majeſty, which they would declare in the preſence of the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſaid Proceeding, being quite and clean contrary to the accuſtomed Formes on the like Caſes, <hi>conſtrained</hi> the <hi>Heſſian</hi> Ambaſſadours to repair to the King, and the <hi>Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgers</hi> to ſee the Commiſſioners, and of their own accords to tell them, That they could not conſent to, nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the ſame; and that they ſhould think themſelves very unfortunate, to be made uſe of in ſuch a tickliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture, to engage his Electoral Highneſſe of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi>'s Ambaſſadours in ſo ill a contrived conference, and meeting. But all their Offices and the Endeavours which they uſed, proved uſeleſs. And the laſt Anſwer which was returned to them, <hi>ſpecified</hi> very particularly; <hi>That it muſt and ſhould be ſo, and that his Majeſty uſed not theſe kind of Proceedings without juſt cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereupon the Ambaſſadours wrote unto the Count of <hi>Slippenbach</hi> (annexed and marked
<note n="f" place="margin">Proof 6.</note>) and told him, That ſince his Majeſty did continue to refuſe them an audience, and that the dignity and reputation of their Maſter, did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their longer ſtay in a place, where they were treated with ſo much ſcorn, they deſired him once more, to know of his Majeſty, whether he would command them any thing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:133421:7"/>back to the Prince Elector their Maſter, and for the laſt time to ſupplicate the King, to vouchſafe them that audience, which they had ſo earneſtly and often intreated.</p>
            <p>The Count returned them an anſwer the ſame day at night being the 23th, and ſent them word (annexed and marked
<note n="g" place="margin">Proof 7.</note>.) That having ſhewn the King their Letter, his Majeſty witneſſed, That he made difficulty to admit them to an audience, untill ſuch time as they had power to reconcile and ſettle the former amity; without which he could not admit of the ſaid Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie, nor make a diſtinction between a declared Enemy, and a Prince, who was entred into a league with his Enemies.</p>
            <p>Whereupon, The Ambaſſadours, perceiving that there was nothing more to be expected for them, they took their leaves of the Ambaſſadors of the Electorall Colledge, and of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of <hi>Lunenburg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe;</hi> and telling them, That they ſhould be guilty and reſponſible for all thoſe things which might happen to the prejudice and diſhonour of the dignity of his Electorall Highneſs their Maſter, in caſe they ſhould any longer ſtay, waiting upon the King: they therefore departed from <hi>Flensburg</hi> on the 24th. of <hi>June,</hi> betimes in the morning; and at their departure they left a Letter with their Hoſt (an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed and marked
<note n="h" place="margin">Proof 8.</note>,) by which the Baron of <hi>Suerin,</hi> ſent word to the Earl of <hi>Slippenbach,</hi> That with a great deal of reluctancy he departed from a place, where he had hoped to have met with an occaſion to have laid a ſtable and firme foundation of an eternall Peace between the Princes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom; but ſince he had ſent him word, that his Majeſty deſired he ſhould be accompanied with a more ample Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and Commiſſion, then that which he had brought along with him; he deemed it fitting to retire himſelf with his Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>league to <hi>Hamborow,</hi> there to expect his Electorall Highneſs further Orders.</p>
            <p>True it is, that one of the Kings Trompeters was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately ſent after the Ambaſſadours, who overtook them at <hi>Rensbough,</hi> where he delivered them a Letter (annexed and marked
<note n="i" place="margin">Proof 9.</note>.) by which the Commiſſioners ſent them word, That they had been the more ſurpriſed at their precipitated departure,, in as much as the Ambaſſabours of <hi>Lunenburg</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:133421:7"/>and <hi>Heſse,</hi> had the day before declared, That the Conference it ſelf was not ſo much objected againſt, as the interv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning of other ſtrange Ambaſſadours, and that his Majeſty having condeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended that they ſhould have a private meeting; they deſired the Ambaſſadours either to return back again, or to repair to ſome neutrall place where the Treaty might be begun.</p>
            <p>And upon the ſaid Letter, the Ambaſſadours might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily have reſolved to have returned to <hi>Flensbourg,</hi> had it not been accompanied by another Paper (annexed and marked
<note n="k" place="margin">Proof 10.</note>.) which made them ſee; That not only they could not expect any good from the ſaid Conference, but that alſo they were looked upon as Heralds, who rather came to declare warre, then like Ambaſſadours from a Prince, who only ſeemed to deſire Peace. Wherefore they contented themſelves to return this anſwer to the Letter (annexed and marked
<note n="l" place="margin">Proof 11.</note>.) Declaring, That they wondred, they were blamed for parting from <hi>Flenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> after they had made ſo long a ſtay there, and had not ſeen the King, and not ſo much as perceived any appearance to be treated, or dealt withall, according to the Dignity of their Character.</p>
            <p>And being arrived at <hi>Hamburrough,</hi> they returned a more ample anſwer unto the ſaid Commiſſioners Letters, and alſo unto the Writing which was ſent unto them (annexed and marked
<note n="m" place="margin">Proof 12.</note>.) and told them, That however they were reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have expected his Electorall Highneſs commands in that place; yet having maturely reflected on what the ſaid Commiſſioners had ſent them, they deemed it requiſite to give his ſaid Electorall Highneſs a verball account thereof, and to receive his poſitive Order thereon.</p>
            <p>But at their return to, and arrivall at <hi>Berlin,</hi> they found the <hi>Prince Elector</hi> ſo well advertiſed of the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, as that he would not permit his ſaid Miniſters to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn towards him: but to the contrary, he cauſed them to ſend the Writing which you will finde annexed at the end of this Relation (marked
<note n="n" place="margin">Proof 13.</note>.) unto the ſaid Commiſſioners, in anſwer to their former exhibited Paper.</p>
            <p>And to the end that no man may have cauſe to doubt of the truthes afore-ſpecified, and that all the world may be the better
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:133421:8"/>able to judg of his ſaid <hi>Electorall Highneſs proceedings, and of his willingneſs and affectionate deſires to the begetting of a Peace, whileſt the Swedes did endeavour to ingage him in a new Warre againſt his own Countrey;</hi> we have thought good to add hereunto thoſe <hi>Proofs</hi> which we have before alledged; and we ſhall remit our ſelves to the judgment of all diſintereſſed and unconcerned perſons, <hi>Whether on the one part, there be not a great deal of reaſon to blame the proceedings of thoſe who make a mocking ſtock of God, and of the whole world, by uſing of his Name, to colour their violences and outragious dealings? and on the other part, there be not a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated conſtraint, to take up Arms, in, and for the defence of ones Countrey, the preſervation of the Empire, and the maintenance of the bonour of the German Nation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the true and entire knowledg which we have of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parties intentions, hath engaged us to divulge this unto the world, and to communicate unto all men theſe enſuing Proofs, which have been copied out of the very orginall Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters themſelves.</p>
            <div n="1" type="proof">
               <head>The firſt Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="a."/>
               </head>
               <head>His Electorall Highneſs of <hi>Brandenburgs</hi> Letter to the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt Serene and Puiſſant King, my moſt honoured Couſen, and Brother.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Had well hoped, that your Majeſty having ended the Denmark Warre, would have cauſed the Treaty with <hi>Poland</hi> to have been ſet on foot, and that you would have authorized the ſame by your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: But having heard that your Majeſty was paſſed into <hi>Sweden,</hi> I would not omit by this occaſion to give you a viſit, by this Letter humbly and amicably to requeſt you, to remember your promiſe, and without any further delayes, to cauſe the Treaties of Peace with <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to be advanced; your Majeſty hath made me hope it ſhould be effected, and have ſo often promiſed it me, as that having abſolutely aſſured it to all the intereſſed parties, I hope you will diſingage the promiſes which I have made unto them thereon: and foraſmuch as my preſervation and aſſurance doth entirely depend upon the speedy
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:133421:8"/>concluſion of the ſaid Treaty, you Majeſty cannot doubt but that I will contribute what lieth in me to accompliſh the ſame; ſo likewiſe ſhall I alwayes preſerve a moſt ſincere Friendſhip for your Majeſty and the Crown of <hi>Sweden;</hi> which I alſo know is the intention of the King and Crown of <hi>Poland.</hi> I remain—Signed thus; Your Majeſties moſt humble Brother and Servant</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>FREDERICK WILLIAM Elector.</signed>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Collen</hi> on the <hi>Spree,</hi> 
                     <date>the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proof">
               <head>The ſecond Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="b."/>
               </head>
               <head>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s Anſwer to his Electoral Highneſſes Letter.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Moſt ſerene Prince Elector, welbeloved Couſen and Brother:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>YOur Letters of the 10th of <hi>March,</hi> were ſafely delivered to me, and I do thereby perceive, not only the paſſion which you bear towards the advancement of the Peace of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but that you do aſſure me, I ſhall meet with the ſame affection and ſincerity in the King of <hi>Poland</hi>'s intentions; but likewiſe ſee the paines you do promiſe, to take in the promoting of ſo godly a work, and the Amity and Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which you tell me, you will conſtantly preſerve for my Perſon and my Crown: wherefore I would not omit to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the ſaid Letter, and to tell you, as your good Friend and Couſen, That you do know I have long ſince nominated Commiſſioners to treat on the Peace of <hi>Poland;</hi> and that I have given them ſufficient inſtructions, and full power, as well before, as ſince the Concluſion of the Treaty with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and expreſs Orders, inceſſantly to labour in the promoting of ſo good a work: Inſomuch, that it is neither mine nor my Miniſters faults (who were alwaies ready to proceed, being ſufficiently impowered) that the Peace of <hi>Poland,</hi> and of its Allyes, hath not long ſince been concluded: But the inſolent and arrogant anſwers which the <hi>Polanders</hi> returned to the Ambaſſadour <hi>de Lombres,</hi> touching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:133421:9"/>the ſaid Pacification, hath given me cauſe to believe, That they harbour a quite contrary deſign, then to make a Peace. Inſomuch, as that I am obliged to pitty thoſe who give cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to what the <hi>Polanders</hi> do averre thereon, whileſt in their hearts they harbour no other deſignes, ſave to oppreſs and ruine others; and whileſt their Councils only tend to the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inating of the neighbouring Provinces. Moreover, you may reſt aſſured, that during my abſence, nothing was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or neglected, which might tend to the ſaid advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Peace, ſince my Commiſſioners (who were fully inſtructed and furniſhed with ſufficient powers) might have done the ſame things, and even more then I my ſelf could, had I been preſent; as it doth plainly appear, by thoſe Declarations which I have thereon made, and which may alſo be eaſily perceived by the very nature of all the ſaid Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiations. Wherefore you may with more reaſon, make your applications to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and repreſent unto him, <hi>as you do very wiſely alledge it in the ſaid Letter;</hi> How much it doth concern you, that the ſaid <hi>Peace be forthwith concluded.</hi> Beſides which, you may remain aſſured, That I have with ſo much the more joy, ſeen the Proteſtation which you do make of the continuance of your friendſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my Perſon and Crown; as that lately it was reported to the contrary: And that they would needs make me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, That you had harboured, and taken reſolutions very prejudicial to the good of my Affairs. However, I alwaies conceived, That being convinced in your conſcience of the ſincerity of my intentions, and that being fully perſwaded of the affection which I bear towards the preſervation of your Perſon, and of your Eſtates, you could not poſſibly be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred capable to give ear to thoſe things which might be told you, nor believe thoſe things which might be averred unto you to the contrary; farre leſs, to change that Friendſhip whereof you have ſo often given me ſuch great aſſurances: But that you would have a great deal of reaſon to imploy all kind of meanes, to the end, that <hi>by Propoſals of a reaſonable and advantagious Peace,</hi> I may be delivered from ſo great a number of Enemies, as do on all ſides declare themſelves
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:133421:9"/>againſt me. You do know, that I have ſeveral times in writing, aſſured you of the conſtancy of my friendſhip; which makes me beleeve, that on your part, you will retain the ſame inclination to cultivate it, and to relinquiſh thoſe things which may either alter or deſtroy the ſame: Finally, I do not doubt but that the Almighty will continue to bleſs my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, will confound the counſels of my enemies, and will diſpoſe the hearts of my neighbours to Peace, and to a reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able agreement. It is that which I deſire with all my heart; to the end that Peace being ſetled in our neigbourhood, my Subjects may enjoy that tranquillity, which I do endeavour to procure them. The good God preſerve you many year, and grant you a perfect health and all proſperity. From <hi>Gotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> the 10th. of <hi>April.</hi> 1658. Signed thus</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your dilections, Friend, Brother, and Couſen, CHARLES GUSTAVE.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>In caſe you would be pleaſed to explain your ſelf a little more upon the preſent conjuncture of Affairs, unto my Reſident in your Court, or unto any other of my Miniſters in <hi>Pomerania,</hi> untill ſuch time as I ſhall be returned to the Army (which will be ſuddainly) you will extreamly oblige me.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proof">
               <head>The third Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="c."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Lord of <hi>Slippenbach</hi>'s Letter to the Baron of <hi>Suerin.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord the Baron,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THe zeal which I do bear to the ſervice of his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the part which I do take in his concernments, do give me the liberty to write unto him, and to beſeech him, not to fail in the ſending of your Excellence in good time towards his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of <hi>Sweden:</hi> I have thereunto added my thoughts on the preſent conjuncture of affairs, although it be not neceſſary to ſend water to the Sea; I have ſeen, not long ſince, in <hi>Furmans Almnack,</hi> that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:133421:10"/>the Moneth of <hi>May,</hi> doth promiſe a great deal of good luck to the read Eagle, and I am perſwaded that it doth ſignifie nought elſe, ſave the reconciliation of his Electoral Highneſſe, and the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cementing of his Friendſhip with the King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> after which, I doubt not but all the world will ſend and complement him, on the good conduct, wherewith all he ſhall have provided for the preſervation of his Eſtates: God grant this good work may be effected. I beſeech your Excellency to ſend me word, about what time you do intend to ſet forwards, that ſo I may meet you by the way: I deſire you alſo not to mention former Treaties, aſſuring you, That we ſhall no ſooner have entered upon a Negotiation, but his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall therein find his aſſurance and contentedneſſe; and by what I ſee in the Copy of the Letter which his Majeſty doth write unto his Electoral Highneſſe, which I have juſt now received: I dare ſay, That there is not a happier Prince then his ſerene High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I remain your Excellencies moſt humble Servant, Signed thus;</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>CHRISTOPHER CHARLES de SLIPPENBACH.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="proof">
               <head>The fourth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="d."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Elector of <hi>Brandenbourg</hi>'s Ambaſſadours Reply to the Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh Commiſſioners notification of a Conference.</head>
               <p>THe Prince Elector of <hi>Brandenbourg</hi>'s Ambaſſadours, do kiſs the hands of the <hi>Lord Preſident,</hi> of Mr. <hi>Kley,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ehrenſtein,</hi> and do make known unto them; That ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reflected upon the advice which they received from them, and that having ſound by their Inſtructions, that his Electorall Highneſs doth expreſly ordain them to demand audience of the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> himſelf; and having more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over pondred, how that it is not the cuſtome of Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours, to enter into any Conferences before they have had audience; they beſeech them, not only to excuſe them, in that they cannot condeſcend thereunto, but alſo to make their excuſes thereon to his Majeſty; and to know of him, when it may pleaſe him to give them audience; ſince his Electorall Highneſs would have juſt occaſion to be diſpleaſed with them, in caſe they ſhould ſuffer themſelves, to be deluded thus any longer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="proof">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:133421:10"/>
               <head>The fifth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="e."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Swediſh Commiſſioners Anſwer, to the Brandenburg Ambaſſadours refuſing a particular Conference.</head>
               <p>THe Deputies nominated by the King, do kiſs the Brandenburg Ambaſſadours hands; and do give them notice, that his ſaid Majeſty, reflecting on his Electorall Highneſſe, being ſo farre enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with his Enemies, as that he accounts him a common Enemy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hath deemed it neceſſary to cauſe certain Propoſitions to be made unto them; which are no other ſave ſuch, as (according to the cuſtom of all Nations, ought to be made before they are admitted to the hearing; which they have deſired, becauſe that the granting of the ſame doth depend partly thereon, ſo that the ſaid Ambaſſadours, may dispoſe themſelves to hear the ſaid Propoſitions, in the preſence of the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of <hi>Lunenburg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe,</hi> as well as the other Orders which they have received from his Majeſty, to communicate unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="proof">
               <head>The ſixth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="f."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Baron of <hi>Suerin</hi>'s Letter to the Earl of <hi>Slippenbach.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord the Count,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE had reaſon to beleeve, that his Electorall Highneſs Embaſſie, which is an unqueſtionable proof of the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of his intentions, and of his reall inclinations to a Peace, would have been the more acceptable to the King, by reaſon that his Majeſty being as yet at <hi>Gottenborow,</hi> had witneſſed unto him, that he would be very glad thereof, and that he cauſed the Prince Palatine of <hi>Sultsbach,</hi> to invite us to come unto this Town: But we are much aſtoniſhed to finde the contrary: Nor ſhall we inlarge upon all the other circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which gives us cauſe to beleeve it; only we cannot any longer diſſemble, that we are very much ſurpriſed at the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties which are made, in the giving of us a hearing; it is become the common diſcourſe in all companies, and people do talk of it about the ſtreets, in ſo much as this refuſall to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:133421:11"/>us to audience, being extreamly prejudiciall to his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Highneſs: we are conſtrained to beſeech your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to do us the favour, to know of his Majeſty, whether he hath any thing to command us unto his Electorall High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; foraſmuch as we ſhall not be able to excuſe our longer ſtay in this place to his Electorall Highneſs, ſince we ſee no appearance at all of effecting any thing here: We have ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny reaſons which debarre us from entring into any conference with the Kings Commiſſioners in the preſence of the Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg and Heſſian Ambaſſadours, as that we doubt not, but they will be capable to ſatisfie his Majeſty, and to oblige him to condeſcend to the audience which we have demanded: but ſince we are again preſſed thereunto, and that in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as we can by no means condeſcend unto, being altogether unuſuall and irregular; we dare not ingage our ſelves in a buiſneſs, which is without a preſident, unleſs we had his Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Highneſſes expreſs Order for the ſame: Wherefore we moſt humbly beſeech your Excellency, not to preſs us any farther thereunto, whereon we ſhall expect your ſpeedy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and proffer unto you our moſt humble ſervice, as being</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble ſervants, OTTON Baron of <hi>Suerin,</hi> and D. WEYMAN.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>Since we cannot be admitted to deliver this Letter our ſelves, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you to put it into his Majeſties hands.</p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="proof">
               <head>The ſeaventh Proof.</head>
               <head>The Earl of <hi>Slippenbachs</hi> Anſwer to the Baron of <hi>Suerin.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord Baron:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Hhave ſhown his Majeſty the Letter which your Excellency wrote uuto me, and the King told me he made a difficulty to give you audience, becauſe you had not power to treat on the reeſtabliſhing of the Friendſhip, betwixt his Majeſty and his Electorall Highneſs; without which his Majeſty cannot reſolve to admit of this Embaſſie,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:133421:11"/>nor make a difference between a declared Enemy, and an Ally of his Enemies, and as the <hi>Romanes</hi> ſay: <hi>The dignity of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth permits not that the Ambaſſadours of Enemies be heard in the Senate.</hi> For in caſe you intend to speak of the Peace of <hi>Poland,</hi> and the other intereſſed Parties, you take upon your ſelves the quality of Mediators; which is a thing inconſiſtent with that alliance, which hath been made with his Majeſties Enemies: In caſe you mean to propound conditions of Peace, and at the ſame time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that if we accept not of them, you will be obliged to remain united with <hi>Poland,</hi> and to put that Treaty in execution which you have made with that Crown; you muſt needs become Judges, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Heralds, by declaring warre againſt us. Wherefore his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty will ot hearken to any Propoſals, ſave ſuch as may conduce to a particular Peace, and may advance the reestabliſhing of the friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip betwixt his Majeſty and his Electorall Highneſs; becauſe the Peace of <hi>Poland</hi> muſt be negotiated by Mediators, and not by ſuch as have taken party, and declared themſelves: You know how I have alwayes aſſured you, That notwithſtanding all what is paſt, his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would be glad to ſee you, in caſe you came accompanied with power to cement the former Friendſhip, and to quit the alliance of his Enemies: But ſeeing in lieu of coming hither upon that account, we know, that ſince your departure from <hi>Berlin,</hi> the enterchangeably delivery of the Treaty, made with the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> hath been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: That the Gunpowder, which his Majeſty ſent into <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> hath been ſtopt at the <hi>Pilliw:</hi> That a Garriſon hath been put into <hi>Frawenburg;</hi> and that ſince all other things have been done, whereon his Majeſty hath reaſon to be ill ſatisfied; he will determinately know, what he is to trust to from the Elector: Whereunto his Majeſty doth add, That in caſe you will yet ſend for a Power, to confer upon a particular Treaty, he will nominate Commiſsioners and Deputies on his behalf, who ſhall meet in any neutrall place, ſuch a one as ſhall be agreed upon: but that otherwiſe he is fully reſolved, not to admit you to an audience; nor to receive any thing on the behalf of a Prince who is entred into an alliance with his Enemies. I am grieved to the heart, when I do reflect upon the preſent conjuncture of affairs, and when I conſider that labyrinthe, wherein his Electorall Highneſs hath engaged himſelf, by the conference at <hi>Bromberg,</hi> and by the aſſembly of ſo many Ambaſſadours, as were lately at <hi>Berlin;</hi> God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:133421:12"/>grant, that the iſſue thereof may prove a reeſtabliſhing of the Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with his Majeſty, a renouncing of the alliance with his Enemies; without which I cannot well ſee how poſsibly his Electorall Highneſs can eſcape the dangers and diſorders wherewithall he is threatned, although one moitie of the world ſhould riſe up in arms againſt us, but few of them ſhould paſſe into <hi>Sweden</hi> with us: I beſeech you but to reflect on the alliance which you have made; whether the victories it may produce, will advance the glory of God, the ſetling of the Proteſtant Religion, or the aſſurance of his Electorall Highneſs: I know that one day you will be mindfull of me. I hope and wiſh to remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble Servant, <hi>Signed</hi> CHRISTOPHER CHARLES SLIPPENBACH.</signed>
                  <dateline>Dated from <hi>Flensburg</hi> 
                     <date>the 23. <hi>June</hi> 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="proof">
               <head>The Eighth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="h."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Barron of <hi>Suerin</hi>'s ſecond Letter to the Count <hi>Slippenbach.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lord the Count,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>ALthough I have occaſion to be glad to take my ſelf home-wards, after ſo diſpleaſing a Voyage, ſince I ſee by your Excellencies former Letter. That his Majeſty will not at all change the reſolution, he hath taken, to refuſe us audience: yet I am conſtrained to confeſſe, that I never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from any place, with ſo much regret, as I had to leave this Town; <hi>by reaſon that no ear would be given to the generall Peace, of which I had well hoped to have here laid the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations.</hi> I dare yet hope, that God, who hath the hearts of Kings in his keeping, will alſo move his Majeſty, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, to preferre an honourable and advantagious Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a deſtructive War to all <hi>Chriſtendome:</hi> And ſince your Excellency ſpecifieth in your Letter, certain particulars upon which his Majeſty deſireth we may have more ample in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, I am reſolved to retire my ſelf, with my Collegue to <hi>Hambourg,</hi> whence we ſhall diſpatch an expreſs to his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> and there expect his Orders, which we
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:133421:12"/>will not fail to communicate unto you. And thus taking leave of you, I remain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Flensbourg</hi> 
                     <date>the 24 of <hi>Jun.</hi> 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>THe Ambaſſadours of the Electoral Colledge told us yeſterday, that his Majeſty was reſolved to take his march through the Markequiſate of <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> I humbly beſeech your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency to remonſtrate unto his ſaid Majeſty, the diſorders which will accrew thereby, and to endeavour to direct him from that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution: For as the ſaid March, muſt needs be to the prejudice of his Electoral Highneſſes Subjects, ſo he is not at all obliged to permit the ſame. He hath hetherto moſt religiouſly kept and obſerved the Peace, and is reſolved ſo to do: But if there be a pleaſure taken in the breaking of it with us, he will rely upon God and the Emperour, who will not fail him. If there remains any thing elſe to be made known unto us, it may be ſent to us in writing to <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg.</hi>
                  </p>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="proof">
               <head>The ninth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/>
               </head>
               <head>The King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s Commiſſioners Letter to the Prince Elector of <hi>Brandenbourg</hi>'s Ambaſſadours.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>My Lords,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>WE were the more ſurpriſed at your precipitated depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by reaſon it bereaved us of the occaſion to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe unto you, by the Kings Order, thoſe meanes, which without all doubt, might have prepared the way to an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodation, and to a Peace, had they not been avoided: as ſoon as we underſtood yeſterday by the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe,</hi> That the conference it ſelf diſtaſted you not ſo much, as their intervention, his Majeſty was pleaſed to have ſo much complaiſance, as to conſent that they ſhould not be preſent: Wherefore we had reſolved this morning, to have given you a viſit without them: So that we cannot imagine why you ſhould ſhun the ſaid conference, when as this Objection was removed. But for as much as his Majeſty doth alwaies paſſionately deſire to make Peace, and to give
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:133421:13"/>
                  <hi>Chriſtendome</hi> reſt, we thought it our duties to fend unto you that, which we had Orders to tell you by word of mouth, and to leave it with you in writing: you will thereby ſee, that there hath not any thing been done, ſave what was very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite, and which ought not to have been done in the like conjunctures; and you will thereby acknowledge the ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of our intentions: Inſomuch, as that you will be obliged to avouch, that you cannot blame us, but your ſelves, in caſe it taketh not effect; We remit our ſelves to your choice; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to return, or nominate a Neutrall Place, where we may begin our Negotiations; his Majeſty doth ſufficiently manifeſt by this Declaration, that he will permit the Treaty to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun; and after you ſhall have ſhewn ſufficient power for the ſame, he will do all whatſoever can be expected from him, for the re-eſtabliſhing of that friendſhip which his Electoral Highneſs hath declined and violated, by ſeveral acts of Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. We remain</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>My LORDS,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your humble Servants, <hi>Signed</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>DAVID MEVIUS,</item>
                        <item>SUEDER DIDERICH KLEY,</item>
                        <item>EDUARD ERNSTEIN.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>Dated from <hi>Elensbourg</hi> on <date>the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="proof">
               <head>The tenth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="k."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Propoſition which was ſent in writing by the Swediſh Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners after the <hi>Brandenbourg</hi> Ambaſſadours.</head>
               <p>IT is moſt aſſured, that the Law of Nature, and the Cuſtomes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by all people, do permit a Sovereign to receive and Treat Ambaſſadours, according to the quality and deſerts of thoſe Princes, by whom they are ſent, and according to the nature of the buiſneſs whereon they are to Treat; wherefore his Majeſty believes, that it cannot be ill taken, if by vertue of that liberty, which is as free to him as to all other Kings, he doth conſtitute Commiſſioners, and cauſeth a Propoſition to be made to the <hi>Brandenbourg</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours: The which he deemed the more requiſite to be done, by reaſon that the Prince their Maſter, hath made it appear, that he will not be his friend. For although that his ſerene Electoral Highneſs did
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:133421:13"/>deſire and ſeek for the alliance with his Majeſty, from the very time that deliberations were as yet but on foot in <hi>Sweden;</hi> whether or no the Poliſh War ſhould be undertaken: and that his ſaid High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, did not only encourage his Majeſty to this enterprize, but alſo promiſed by a formall Treaty, his Aſiſtances and Forces againſt <hi>Poland:</hi> However, all the world doth know, That he hath renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the ſaid alliance with his Majeſty: It was to have been perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, and undiſſolvable, but his Electoral Highneſſe rent it aſunder without any neceſſity, which might not, at leaſt, have been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spene't withall, ſince he might have avoided the ſame, by doing or by ſuffering that to be done, which would have been very feazible; and not at all regarding the particular favour which his Majeſty did him, to offer him a neutrallity upon ſuch reaſonable conditions, as would not have been prejudicial to his Majeſties affairs: And as if it were a ſmall matter to contract to friendſhip with a declared ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of his firſt Allyes, his Electoral Highneſs ceaſed not therewith neither, but paſſed on further, and hath made a League, in which the King is treated, and ſtiled, the common enemy. He promiſeth his favour and aſſiſtance to the Kings declared enemies, not only in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> but alſo in the Empire; and beſpeaks his ſhare of thoſe Conqueſts which are pretended to be made in thoſe States which his Majeſty did and doth there poſſeſſe, contrary to the expreſs promiſe which he had made to his Majeſty, to be aſſiſting unto him in the defence thereof, with all his might, againſt all Parties whatſoever; which appears manifeſtly by the Articles of the Treaty which was Negotiated and at <hi>Velau,</hi> and finally concluded and ſigned at <hi>Brom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Electoral Highneſs,</hi> after he had held private intelligence with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> entred upon a Negotiation with him, during the ſame time when as the King had declared War againſt him, and whileſt his Armies were in thoſe Kingdomes; he exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> to continue the War, and to reject Peace; not contenting himſelf to encourage him herein, but alſo promiſing him a speedy relief, and to make a powerfull diverſion in thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces where his Majeſty had his Armies: All which Treaty was carried on at <hi>Coppenhagen</hi> by the ſame Ambaſſadour, who had proferred his Princes Mediation to procure a Peace between <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark;</hi> although ſince, it was continued by another, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:133421:14"/>finally concluded at <hi>Cologne</hi> on the <hi>Spreé.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to compaſs this promiſed relief, a more powerfull eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was requiſite, wherefore a Negotiation was commenced with the moſt ſerene King of <hi>Hungary</hi> for an alliance; which at firſt was only to have been defenſive, but afterwards came to an offenſive one, which was speedily concluded and compleated with ſo much animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, as that not only his Majeſty was therein treated as the common enemy of <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> but alſo the Treaty was filled with all that poſſibly could be alledged againſt the greateſt Enemies thoſe Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyes had; and it was reſolved, not only to ſet upon thoſe places which his Majeſty had in <hi>Poland,</hi> but alſo to take and ſhare amongſt the ſaid Allyes, thoſe Provinces which do belong unto him in the Empire.</p>
               <p>Nor did his Electoral Highneſſe remain ſatisfied, to permit theſe particulars to be ſet down in writing, but did alſo paſs on to commit acts of hoſtility, as followeth: He gave paſſage and Proviſions to the <hi>Polanders,</hi> and ſuffered them to over-run, pillage, and burn <hi>Pomerania;</hi> he hindered thoſe Leagues which his Majeſty cauſed to be made in the Empire, although the ſame are permitted unto all Princes indifferently, ſeeing they were not burdenſome to any one; and that they were only to be imployed in the defence of his Territories: He commanded his Subjects to quit his Majeſties ſervice, againſt the Liberties which the Lawes of the Empire give them: he cauſed to be ſtopt in the Haven of <hi>Pillou,</hi> thoſe Powders and other Muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of War, and Proviſions which the King had ſent to his Places in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> contrary to the Treaty of alliance, and againſt the Law of Nations; and he oppoſed himſelf in the Aſſembly of the Lower <hi>Circle</hi> of <hi>Saxony,</hi> unto that ſecurity which the Eſtates of that <hi>Circle</hi> were obliged to give him againſt the invaſion of the King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> crying down his Majeſties actions, and teſtifying his hatred and malice, by animating and ſtirring up all the world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, as againſt the common enemy; at ſuch a time when as his Electoral Highneſs had not any occaſion to complain of his ſaid Majeſty, but when the King did give him the greateſt proof of his Friendſhip and good will.</p>
               <p>All men do know, and it is moſt aſſured, that his Electoral Highneſſe hath promiſed the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> relief, that he hath ſollicited the conjunction of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Armies; and that to this end, the Forces of the Allies did often ſhew themſelves in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:133421:14"/>when as there did not any enemy at all appear, and when as there was not any thing at all to be apprehended: That he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired aſiſtance from all parts, as againſt a declared enemy; and that he had endeavoured to render the Kings beſt actions odious: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as it is void of all doubt, but that he would abſolutely have declared himſelf, had it not been for the Juſtice and Proſperity of his Majeſties Armies.</p>
               <p>And although theſe undeniable Proofs (which have been but too much confirmed by the publick report of them) did manifeſt his Electoral Highneſs ill intentions, yet his Majeſty never changed his good will, which he ever bore towards one who threatned him, although he leaſt deſerved it; having declared whileſt he was yet at <hi>Gottenbourg,</hi> that in caſe his Electoral Highneſſe would depute any of his Miniſters towards him, accompanied with ſufficient Power to cement and ſettle the former Friendſhip again, his Majeſty would alwaies be found willing to embrace the ſame.</p>
               <p>But his Electoral Highneſs was ſo farre from anſwering theſe Teſtimonies of Friendſhip, that, notwithſtanding the foregoing Declarations; and as ſoon as his Ambaſſadours were departed <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> he did ratifie that Treaty which was made with the moſt ſerene King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> againſt his Majeſty, as againſt a common enemy; did again cauſe to be arreſted in the <hi>Pillau,</hi> thoſe Powders and Amunitions which were ſent to the Royal <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and did put a Garriſon in <hi>Frawenberg,</hi> which the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> had abandoned, although he had no title to the ſame; and that according to the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties between the King and the Elector, and according to the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Lawes, that place ought to have remained in the Kings poſſeſſion: however, he refuſed to admit the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Troops into the ſame, cauſed the Officers to be purſued, filled the Aſſemblies with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints; without cauſe of Juſtice, ſent to demand aide from all Parts, as againſt a declared enemy; and did all he could, to manifeſt his diſaffection and ill will, and the ſmall inclination he bore to the Peace.</p>
               <p>Inſomuch, as that the King finding himſelf obliged to aſſure him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his Electoral Higneſs intentions, and to know whether he was to Treat with the Ambaſſadours of a Prince, in Peace, or at enmity; (ſince by what we have before alledged, it could not otherwiſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:133421:15"/>be conceived;) he thought, that by vertue of the Law of Nations, and the Cuſtomes admitted by all Kings and people, to name Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, who might Penetrate into the Princes intentions, who might know the ſubject of the Embaſsy; and who might ſee the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours power, before he reſolved (during this uncertainty) whether he ſhould admit them or no. True it is, that his Majeſty permitted the Ambaſſadours to come to this Town, but not with an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent thereby to tye up his own hands, and to forego that freedom which he hath, to cauſe the neceſſary Precautions to take place. To the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, without their coming hither, how could we have learn't of them thoſe things which we deſired to know? And we could not have told how to have regulated thoſe things which were requiſite, before we proceeded to a Negotiation; to the end, we might judge by the nature of thoſe affairs, wherewith they were intruſted, in what manner we ſhould Treat them: and thereon, to reſolve, whether or no, in the audience which ſhould afterwards be granted unto them, they ſhould be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered either as Friends or Enemies: As alſo, to reſolve, whether the Dignity of the King, and the Preſent ſtate of affairs, would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to receive them at all.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Brunswick, Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> were come in the behalf of their Superiours, to proffer their Mediations, it was thought good to invite tdem to be preſent at the Conference; to the end, they might be Witneſſes of the Juſtice, Sincerity, and Integrity, whereon we ſhould have proceeded on his Majeſties behalf: We cannon imagine why the Electors Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours would not condeſcend thereunto. They alledge indeed, that it is a thing without a Preſident, contrary to the uſuall Formes and Cuſtomes, and prejudicial to the Dignity of his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But as the Execution of a thing which is juſt and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable in its ſelf, ought not to be hindered, becauſe no example can be alledged thereof: ſo likewiſe ought it to have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that in all this, there is nothing contrary, to what Princes are accuſtomed to do, by profferring their Mediation and good Offices unto two Parties; and that there is nothing in it, which doth repugne the equity or dignity of his Electoral Highneſs, ſince the King hath done all, what in reaſon could be deſired of him, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the prejudicing of his Intereſts.</p>
               <p>But the refuſall which the Ambaſſadours made, to enter into a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:133421:15"/>Conference, in the preſence of a third Party, doth render their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy to be ſuſpected; and the rather, when the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Lunenburg</hi> having deſired to be excuſed (becauſe they foreſaw the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> would not give way thereunto) the King would willingly have ſo much complyance for both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as to exempt them, that ſo no retardment might enſue upon the Treaty.</p>
               <p>Now the chief Point of this our Propoſition, is, That his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty having deemed it fit, before all things, to know the intention of his ſerene Electorſhip, hath commanded us to ask you, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his ſaid Electoral Highneſs, will diſingage himſelf from the Intereſts of his Majeſties Enemies, and renew the Treaties of Peace and Friendſhip, which ſeem to be changed, by thoſe things which we have before alledged; as alſo: to know what power you have to proceed hereon: So ſoon as his Majeſty ſhall be aſſured of the one, and ſhall know that you have ſufficient power for the other, he will immediately give command for the beginning of the Treaties; and in caſe you have not ſufficient Power, his Majeſty permits you to ſtay in this Town, untill ſuch time as you have received them: Or otherwiſe, doth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent that the Treaties may be held in any other Newtrall place; as at <hi>Kiel, Sleſwick,</hi> or <hi>Hambourg:</hi> And as ſoon as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty ſhall have notice thereof, he will nominate Commiſſioners, and will ordain what elſe ſhall be requiſite to cauſe the Treaty to take effect. This is that which we have thought good to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto you, and alſo to aſſure you of our humble ſervices, ſo farre as they ſhall not be repugnant to that Duty which we owe unto our King.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Given at <hi>Flensbourg</hi> on <date>the <hi>23</hi> of June <hi>1658.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="proof">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:133421:16"/>
               <head>The eleventh Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="l."/>
               </head>
               <head>The Ambaſſadours of <hi>Brandenburgs</hi> Letter, in Anſwer to the King of <hi>Swedens</hi> Commiſſioners.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIRS;</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>VVE received thoſe Letters which you wrote unto us from <hi>Flensbourg,</hi> on the 24 <hi>June,</hi> and to tell you the truth, we are in a manner aſtoniſhed, that you ſhould ſend after us, and that we are accuſed to have precipitated our departure; and that likewiſe the fault of all that which hath hapned is caſt upon us: We were ſent, if not at the requeſt, yet at leaſt not againſt the deſire of his Majeſty, by a Prince Elector of the Empire, who is his Kinſman and Neighbour: we were at our arrivall received by his Majeſties Miniſters, and at their requeſt, we drew nigh, as we may ſay, even to the gates of his Court, and, if after our ſo long ſojourning there, (as that we could not any longer have ſtayed, without our detracting from the grandure and dignity of his Electorall Highneſs) we at length departed thence: You may conſider if you pleaſe, that it was a meer conſtraint; and after thoſe unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionable proofs which we had received of the deſign there was to have treated his Electorall Highneſs as a declared Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; which was evident, not only by the generall report there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of which was come to our ears, but alſo by the Expreſs Letters from the Lord of <hi>Slippenbach,</hi> which you will find hereunto an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed; for which we were very ſorry. And thoſe Letters which we have written unto the ſaid Count upon this ſubject, in anſwer unto his, do ſufficiently denote the ſame: but by reaſon they were delivered late enough, and that we aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeve you have not ſeen them, we do think fitting to add thus much, That we ſhall alwayes moſt powerfully ſecond the great inclinations which his Electorall Highneſs harbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth towards a Peace, and towards an accommodation; we ſhall expect his Orders thereon at <hi>Hamborow;</hi> and as ſoon as we ſhall have received them, we will not fail to give you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:133421:16"/>thereof; and ſhall anſwer unto all, what may be expected from</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Dated at <hi>Rensbourg</hi> on <date>the 25. <hi>June.</hi> 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <salute>SIR,</salute> 
                  <signed>&amp;c.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="proof">
               <head>The twelfth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="m."/>
               </head>
               <head>A ſecond Letter from the Brandenburg Ambaſſadours to the Swediſh Commiſsioners.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>SIRS:</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>BEfore we left <hi>Rensbourg,</hi> we returned you an Anſwer to the Letter you wrote unto us from <hi>Flensbourg;</hi> but being on our jouaney, and ready to take Coach, we contented our ſelves only to write the more ſuccinctly unto you, by how much we are perſwaded of the high prudence of the King your Maſter, and therefore do firmly beleeve, that he cannot deſire more at our hands, ſince it muſt needs be evident, that being at ſo great a diſtance from our Court, it was not in our powers to return unto the place from whence we came, but much againſt our wills; and far leſs to engage the intereſt and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Prince our Maſter, in writing, without his Electorall Highneſs expreſs order. Wherefore we were reſolved without any delay, to have repreſented the whole unto him by our Letters; to the end that having received his commands thereon, we might the better have made anſwer from <hi>Hamborow,</hi> to thoſe things which you deſire to know of us.</p>
               <p>We do not deny but that the buiſneſs is of ſo great importance, as that all things ought to have been eſſayed rather then to break, and by a precipitated reſolution, to have fruſtrated the effects of our Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, from which all Chriſtendome might juſtly expect ſo conſiderable an advantage: We ſtill do beleeve the ſame, and therefore we ſhall uſe all poſsible means to juſtifie our proceedings; and to let the world ſee, That if the ſucceſs proves not anſwerable to our deſires, we ſhall at leaſt have ſatisfied our conſciences, by the integrity of our Councils, and the ſincerity of our Intentions.</p>
               <p>But we think our ſelves obliged to give you notice, That having more maturely conſidered on what behoved us to do; we have thought it fitting to change the reſolution which we had taken, to expect his Electorall Highneſs command in this place, conceiving it to be more
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:133421:17"/>expedient that we go to <hi>Berlin</hi> with all speed; becauſe a perſonall negotiation hath ſomething more in it then can be expected to be ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected by writing, and at leaſt we ſhall reap this ſatisfaction by our voyage, that by a speedy and faithfull report of all the buiſneſs, we ſhall bring it to a reſolve without any delay; we doubt not but you will be of the ſame minde, and that conſequently you will take pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and expect ſuch anſwers as we ſhall return unto you, ſo ſoon as we ſhall be arrived at our Court.</p>
               <p>And as to what concerns the buſineſs it ſelf, we have ſeen and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined the writing which you ſent us, together with the Letters; and we hope you have ſo good an opinion of us, as to beleeve that we are not altogether ſo ignorant in the debating of affairs, nor ſo much void of reaſon, but that it would be very eaſie for us to make anſwer to the chief heads of the ſaid Manifeſt; and clearly to demonſtrate, That it is full of Equivocations, of words whoſe ſenſe and meaning are obſcure, and containeth ſeverall things which are as much diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant unto the Piety of our Prince, as from Truth it ſelf: whereof we are ſo well aſſured in our conſciences, as that we are willing to beleeve, That the ſaid Peece was not ſent unto us from the King, nor were thoſe Writings compiled out of the Regiſters of thoſe Perſons, who had an inspection in buiſneſs; but by ſuch as were transported by an unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate precipitation, or by a falſe and ſad preoccupation, without any knowledg at, all of the foregoing paſſages; nor reflecting in the leaſt upon thoſe things which are to enſue; not being ſo diſcreet as to conſider what they did, and were wilfully reſolved to trouble the Peace of Chriſtendome, by new affected quarrels, in ſtead of ſetling and reeſtabliſhing the ſame by new and well grounded alliances. But ſince the Honour of, and even his Electorall Higneſs conſcience, art engaged in this concerment, we ſhall deſire you not to take it ill, that we enter no further thereon at this preſent, but that we leave the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment thereof unto himſelf.</p>
               <p>There is but one thing which we finde our ſelves obliged to touch on, by the by, which is that in your writing, you ſay the King hath chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his reſolution, and that he would have ſo much complaiſance or indulgence (according to the Latin original word, they are your own words) for the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe,</hi> as to dispence with them ſo far, as that they might not entervene at the Meeting or Conference, which he had cauſed to be propounded unto
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:133421:17"/>us: But we crave your pardon, if we averre, that you do maintain with too much aſſurance, a thing which is not ſo: For the ſaid Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours themſelves, and the Kings Ministers, do full well know, as you your ſelves Sirs (who are Perſons of Honour) can teſtifie; that we knew nothing thereof, and that the least word thereon was not told unto us: the laſt Letters from the Lord of <hi>Slippenbach,</hi> and the viſits which were made to the ſaid Ambaſſadours, to take our leaves of them, are manifeſt Proofs to the contrary; and do plainly evidence, that there was no appearance at all for us, to expect an audience, in ſuch a manner as was due unto us; nor that the King would alter the reſolution, which he he had taken, to make us ſerve as an example unto Poſterity; and to expoſe us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an unavoidable affront, ſuch a one, as was not to be repaired, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of treating of us as Ambaſſadours, from a Prince Elector of the Empire.</p>
               <p>But we can with more truth alledge, That we never refuſed to admit of the Ambaſſadours of <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſen;</hi> by reaſon that the ſubject our of Embaſſy, being juſt and plauſible, we had no reaſon at all, to debarre the Miniſters of thoſe Princes from the Cogniſance thereof, who profeſſe a moſt particular friendſhip to our Maſter; neither did we ever hinder the Kings Miniſters from viſiting of us, nor never refuſed to enter into any Conference with them: But we would not, nor could not conſent into a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, the manner, place, and time whereof was preſcribed us. We believed it was not expedient, but very unſeaſonable, becauſe it was to have preceed our audience; beſides, we had reaſon to ſuſpect the ſaid Conference; neither would we acknowledge that ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whereby it was intended to have enforced us thereunto: Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we would not accept of that, which the Ambaſſadours them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could not approve of. For we came not thither to debate, or for to enter into a conteſtation with the Kings Miniſters, but we were there in the quality of Ambaſſadours, for to demand Audience of the King: We appeared there (I ſay) becauſe the King had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired it, and becauſe his Miniſters had invited us thither, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us, had entertained us, and had done us ſeveral other Civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: After all which, not to be admitted unto audience, to have the ſame deferred and delayed, and finally, abſolutely refuſed; which was never yet done by any Prince, who had once received Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:133421:18"/>into his Court, ſince it is to the Perſon of the Prince, and not to his Miniſters, That Ambaſſadours do make their addreſſes. This was the thing at which we were offended, and this was the cauſe why, to our great grief, we departed.</p>
               <p>Nor can you alledge, That we precipitated our ſaid departure, ſince it could eaſily be imagined, that after ſo long a ſtay, we were not like to beg for an audience, which in Juſtice ought not to have been refuſed us.</p>
               <p>But all theſe things are ſo well known unto you, as that we ſhall not need to adde any thing elſe hereunto; being aſcertained in our Conſciences, that you muſt needs acquieſſe unto thoſe Truths, which we have alledged. Moreover, we remain,</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>SIRS,</salute> 
                  <signed>&amp;c.</signed>
                  <dateline>Dated from <hi>Hamborrow</hi> on <date>the <hi>30</hi> of <hi>June 1658.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="proof">
               <head>The thirteenth Proof. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="n."/>
               </head>
               <head>A third Letter from the <hi>Brandenburg</hi> Ambaſſadours, in Anſwer to the Propoſition in writing, ſent after them by the Swediſh Commiſſioners.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Sirs,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>NO Perſon whatſoever, who hath the leaſt inſight and knowledge of the ſtate of our Affairs, can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, That the Piety, and the Intereſt of our Elector, doth oblige him earneſtly to endeavour the generall Peace; and to ſee it maintained, and preſerved throughout all <hi>Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> For all men, who profeſs themſelves to be verſed in the managing of publique affairs, muſt needs avouch; That this <hi>Prince, whoſe Prudence is of as large an extent, as his Provinces,</hi> by intereſting himſelf in the eſtabliſhing of the publique tranquility of the Chriſtian world, doth at the ſame time, include the ſetling of his own private ſecurity; becauſe his Principalities bordering on moſt of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> it is unpoſſible for him to preſerve them, but by his keeping a perfect good intelligence betwixt his Neighbours.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Electoral Highneſs</hi> hath ſo well accompliſhed the ſame,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:133421:18"/>as that being unreproachable upon this account, he thought himſelf not bound to be offended, when by our relation, he heard the ill Treatment, which we received by your King, and ſaw the calumnies, wherewith all he finds himſelf ſlandered, by that Paper which you ſent unto us from <hi>Flensbourgh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>great Prince,</hi> is willing to forget and paſs by the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular wrongs; which are done unto his Perſon, to bewail poor <hi>Germany,</hi> which is like to be involved in new diſorders: However, he cannot chooſe but deteſt the <hi>Ingratitude</hi> of thoſe, <hi>who cloak their pernitious deſignes;</hi> and the rage, by which they endeavour to continue the Warres, by ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt pretentions.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Prince is rendred guilty,</hi> becauſe he hath not quite ruined himſelf for your Kings ſake; and he is threatned with a Warre, becauſe he cannot any longer ſecond an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>ambition,</hi> without the expoſing of his Perſon, and his Dominions, to a finall ruine. And moreover, he is at this preſent, reproached with that, which the King did former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem the moſt of all in him; <hi>when he confeſſed, that he ſhould never be able, to acknowledge thoſe, Obligations, for the which he ſtood engaged to his Electoral Highneſſe:</hi> Juſt as if there were a great deal of advantage to be reaped, by finding out a pretence to ruine a Friend, unto whom a man is over-ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged; and a great deal of glory to be taken, in the pillaging of a Creditours Houſe, thereby to find wherewithall to pay a Debt, which would otherwiſe reman unſolved. They affect to render all the Princes actions odious, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on thoſe things, which he hath formerly done; and inſtead of the diſſembling, or at leaſt, excuſing thoſe things, which might be blamed in the conduct of a Friend, ſo great a pleaſure is taken in the crying down of the ſame; as it ſeemes they are glad to have met with ſomething, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they might frame a pretended quarrell againſt him.</p>
               <p>Neither can it be with any other deſign, that his Electorall Highneſs is accuſed, <hi>To have ſolicited the Warre againſt</hi> Poland; <hi>to have quitted the alliance, without any neceſſity; to have made a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:133421:19"/>new one with</hi> Poland, <hi>and with the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria; <hi>to have endeavored to engage the King of</hi> Denmark <hi>in the ſame; to have promiſed relief to the one, and to have demanded it from the other; to have given paſſage to the enemies; to have recalled his Subjects out of the Kings ſervice; to have hindred his Leagues; to have ſeized the Gunpowders:</hi> and to have done ſeveral other things, without the making of any diſtinction, either of time of places, with as much affectation as injuſtice. It would be a very eaſie matter for us, to reply on all the Accuſations, in ſuch a manner, as thereby we might manifeſt the juſtice of our Cauſe, and the integrity of our Intentions; if ſo be our Prince, who is not capable of our unworthineſs and low actions, had not rather remit himſelf thereon, unto your own Conſciences, then to render you aſhamed, by thoſe Anſwers, which he would return to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches.</p>
               <p>However, we cannot chooſe but tell you, That there is ſo much the leſs appearance of what you alledge; <hi>That his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Highneſſe ſhould have ſought unto you for your alliance, to make War againſt</hi> Poland; as that you cannot tell why he ſhould have done ſo? what advantages he could thereby reape? or what glory he ſhould thereby ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Warre,</hi> certainly cannot be pleaſing, ſave only unto thoſe, who are <hi>transported, either by ambition or covetouſneſſe;</hi> or who through poverty, are conſtrained to live by Thefts, and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other mens Eſtates: Unto ſuch (I ſay) as take a delight amidſt the publick calamities, and eſteem their only tortures to conſiſt in Peace and Tranquility; who reverence vice, and who account of Pillagings, Murders, Violations, Sacriledges, and the other inſeparable diſorders, which are tyed to a Warre, as heroick Vertues, and as qualities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a King. But <hi>our Prince,</hi> was alwaies incapable of ſuch unworthy thoughts: <hi>For he ſucked Piety from his Mothers Breaſts, and he inherited the love of Juſtice, and the fear of God, from his Predeceſſors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We full well know, that thoſe Warres which are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together neceſſary, prove oftentimes the moſt ſaddeſt unto
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:133421:19"/>thoſe who wage them: Wherefore <hi>we did diſſwade the Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian Warre, by divers and ſundry Embaſſies. The Town of</hi> Stetin, <hi>doth very well know, that we abhorre the very thoughts of that Warre, and that we never had a hand therein, but when we were conſtrained thereunto;</hi> which you cannot likewiſe deny, in caſe you do but call to mind, how that the <hi>Polonian Warre</hi> was no ſooner reſolved on, but that at the ſame time, <hi>you reſolved likewiſe to engage the Elector therein, whether he would or not:</hi> And we were ſo farre <hi>from preſſing you to Warre againſt</hi> Poland, <hi>that</hi> Wittenberg <hi>was already entred that Kingdome, when your Ambaſſadours came to this Town, to ſeek unto us, or rather to threaten us, and conſtrain us, to enter into an alliance with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We could hardly believe, that you could have the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to reproach us in this wiſe, unleſs you had had aſſured proof thereof: Wherefore we required to know of thoſe perſons, which make up his Electorall Highneſs Council, whether or no their deliberations could in any wiſe have given cauſe for the ſaid Accuſation: We have runne over the Drafts of all the Letters, which were thereon written, and we have peruſed all our Regiſters, to diſcover, whether hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily your cunning, the neceſſity of thoſe times, and the ſtate of affairs as then (which were capable, to have moved the firmeſt conſtancy, and the reſoluteſt determinations) might have extorted from us, any thing implying the ſame: But we can take God to witneſs, That we could not light upon any thing in the leaſt, <hi>That might cauſe us to ſuſpect our having failed in our fidelity to</hi> Poland, <hi>or of our amity to</hi> Sweden.</p>
               <p>For our <hi>Elector</hi> could never ſufficiently move the entring on a Peace unto all your Ambaſſadours, nor to recommend it unto thoſe, who ſided with <hi>Sweden.</hi> True it is, that <hi>he gave ear to your Propoſitions; That he accepted thoſe advantages, which you proffered him, purpoſely to gain him to your party;</hi> and, <hi>That he did receive your Preſents:</hi> But all this he did <hi>with an upright heart, and on purpoſe to preſerve them for the right owners, leaſt they might fall into the hands of ſtrangers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The refuſall which you made, to condeſcend to a Peace
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:133421:20"/>with <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Warre wherewithall you threatned the <hi>Ducall Pruſſia,</hi> did conſtrain his Electorall Highneſs, to enter into a Negotiation with you; and engaged him in a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, by which he alwaies hoped he might meet with an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſerve you, as well as the <hi>Polanders;</hi> to preſerve both the one and the other, by a good Treaty of Peace, and to give a Teſtimony of his conſtant Fidelity to <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For which purpoſe, our Ambaſſadours were continually with you, and never departed your Court, who inceſſantly preſſed you to come to a Peace, and who amuſed you, whileſt we were not as yet gotten into a poſture to defend our ſelves: However, we ſticked not to take up Armes, to continue our Leagues, and to paſs with our Army into <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> notwithſtanding our oppoſitions and threatnings. You may well remember, Gentlemen, what paſſed as then, and what the Elector did, to endeavour to beget a Peace, or to uphold the juſtice and equity of the <hi>Polonian</hi> Forces, by the conjunction of his own; till ſuch time, as that he ſaw, he could not obtain any thing at your hands, that was juſt, nor overcome your obſtinacy to deſtroy all: Wherefore he rather choſe to expect the very laſt extreamities, then to fail in that Fidelity, wherein this <hi>generous and good Prince</hi> ſtood ingaged to the Crown of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Both the Royal <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the States of the United <hi>Provinces,</hi> can witneſs thoſe endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, which were uſed by his Electorall Highneſs, for to ingage them in an alliance, which might be ſufficient to oppoſe theſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpations:</hi> And we heartily grieve, that the ſucceſs thereof, did not anſwer our Expectations: However, we ſhall alwaies retain this ſatisfaction to our ſelves, <hi>That the Elector never changed his mind, and that he never failed in his duty, but by conſtraint; No not with</hi> Poland <hi>its ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His <hi>Elector all Highneſs,</hi> could have wiſhed withall his heart, to have ſeen the ſaid Kingdome in a better condition: But in regard that the King himſelf had deſerted it; that the Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours had abandoned the management of affairs; that the Souldiers were poſſeſſed with a general cowerdize; that all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:133421:20"/>Subjects were treacherous; and that even thoſe, who were born, and payed to fight in the defence of that Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, had taken up Armes againſt her: He was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, even to give way to thoſe great Evils, which had overwhealmed the whole State.</p>
               <p>Inſomuch, that there cannot be any unbyaſſed dſiinterreſſed party, but will praiſe the Electors prudence, who in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving himſelf, by the meanes of a Treaty, remained in a condition, both to preſerve <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poland</hi> itſelf, is diſcreet and rational enough, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, and to avouch: That all neceſſary meanes are honeſt and lawfull; and that the Obligation of the Lord, and of the Subjects, being reciprocall. The Subject cannot be blamed for having failed, to defend the Lord, in caſe the Lord hath failed to protect the Subject. And wherein <hi>Poland</hi> is more equitable then you are, for being ſenſible of her ſad enforced deſtiny, ſhe bewailes ours; not accuſing us to have quitted her party, becauſe ſhe knows we were conſtrained thereunto; although ſhe likewiſe full well knows; That in caſe the <hi>loſs of the battell of</hi> Warſowe <hi>be not wholly due to our Army, yet at leaſt it did not a little contribute thereunto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, we conjure you <hi>(Gentlemen)</hi> without paſſion, to reflect upon the tye, which lieth upon us to endeavour the begetting and preſerving a Peace between <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> and to maintain their power in a juſt equality; as alſo to judg <hi>how little appearance there is, that we ſhould have obliged your King, to take up Armes againſt</hi> Poland: And whether it be not a very diſhoneſt part to alledge: <hi>That we endeavoured to make an alliance for a Warre, which of neceſſity, muſt have proved de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We only deſire you chiefly to conſider, how and in what matter you can poſſible blame our <hi>reconciliation</hi> with <hi>Poland?</hi> And with what equity the King can condemn our proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings at <hi>Bromberg?</hi> ſeeing he approved of what had paſſed at <hi>Koningsberg.</hi> And truly, ſince you were not aſhamed to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a Law, and a neceſſity on a Prince your Friend, and to conſtrain him to act againſt the Lord of his Mannor, the King ought to harbour ſo much generoſity, as not to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:133421:21"/>to ſee that reunited again by a ſecret deſtiny, which was diſunited by your violence and force. Princes do not proceed like common people: They are not accuſtomed to pick groundleſs quarrels; nor are they tranſported by cholar: Their Fortune is above all that. So likewiſe, <hi>do they not undertake any Warre, but with a reſolution to obtain a Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We were conſtrained to ſide with you, and ſo long as the State of our affairs did permit, as to ſtay by you, we upheld your party with Fidelity, and never abandoned you, till you had deſerted us; and had left us to the diſcretion of Fortune, without either hopes of a Peace, or of a Relief: Nor can you be ignorant in what a condition the Kings Forces were in, when we drew off, after the Battell of <hi>Warſow;</hi> and in what a manner the Enemies recruted themſelves after the ſaid loſs; which inſtead of quite ruining them, reſtored all their affairs, and put a double proportion of courage into them: We found them marching at our heels, when we thought we had laid them along; and we found them pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing us in the reare, laying all waſte, whereſoever they paſt, and putting all to fire and ſword; in their purſuite mena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing us (even after their defeate and flying away) <hi>more like Victors, then overcome men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Tranſilvanian</hi> trembled, the <hi>Muſcovite</hi> threatned us, and the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> thwarted all your deſignes by a new Warre, whereby the King was obliged to abandon the whole, to march unto the relief of the Principality of <hi>Bremn.</hi> In regard whereof, we could not refuſe to hearken unto the Remonſtrances of our Subjects, to the Prayers of our Friends, and to the proffers of our Enemies; or rather, <hi>We were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to make a Peace with</hi> Poland, and to accept of thoſe conditions which were proffered us, although they had been farre leſs equitable then thoſe, which were grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us.</p>
               <p>Now this being the true ſtate of the buiſneſs, <hi>Can you with reaſon alledge, that the Elector abandoned you? Can you with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be diſpleaſed thereat? Are you in a capacity to threaten him?</hi> And can you hinder him to agree with the Enemy? and by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:133421:21"/>a Treaty, to endeavour to preſerve his Eſtates, the which you could not defend. An invincible neceſſity might have induced him, had there been one to have preferred his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt before anothers: But nature it ſelf, even from our Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoods, doth teach us to avoid our own ruine, by all meanes poſſible. That which neceſſitates, doth juſtifie; and where neceſſity reignes, there is no Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For in a ſtorm, each man ſeeks his own preſervation, though to the loſs of other mens goods.</p>
               <p>We confeſs; that the King wiſhed us better luck, and that he uſed all meanes poſſible to retain his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe</hi> on his party; to which end, he cauſed ſeveral Propoſitions to be made: He deſired that we would make uſe of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and he made us hope, he would make Peace with <hi>Poland;</hi> and that he would return to the Army, within ſix weeks time; which proved meer words, and nothing more was intended. But we ſtood in need of effectuall and powerfull relief againſt the enemy, who was already gotten into our Countrey, whileſt the King having <hi>abandoned Pruſſia,</hi> and his other Allyes, was departed from thence, and was order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Affairs in <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Inſomuch, as that all men muſt needs perceive, there was no choice left to be made at that time; and that his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> being not able any longer to reſiſt the ſtrength of neceſſity, was conſtrained to bethink himſelf of minding his own buiſneſs, and to preſerve himſelf by meanes of a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Wherein we only made uſe of the Kings Example, who was farre cunninger then we, when he abandoned his <hi>Conqueſts</hi> in <hi>Poland,</hi> and his <hi>Friends</hi> in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> to <hi>defend his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates in</hi> Germany; rather then other mens any where elſe: But however, he hath been ſo much the more unjuſt, that having failed of his word, through a leſs preſſing neceſſity, he finds fault, that in an utmoſt extreamity, we have followed his Example.</p>
               <p>You would willingly perſwade us, <hi>That we might have avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that neceſsity; by doing, or ſuffering ſuch things to be done, as ought to have been done; and the which would have been very eaſie.</hi> But we attribute this to the good reallity with which you are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:133421:22"/>uſed to proceed in all your other affairs, even to the prejudice of your beſt Friends: Nor can we chooſe but admire the dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whereby you could penetrate ſo deep into our affairs, as not only to diſcover thoſe ſecrets, which we were deſirous to have kept from the knowledg of others; but alſo thoſe which were unknown to our ſelves: But as you have ſo good an opinion of your own buiſneſs, take care you be not deceived in ours: For if every one ought to be beleeved, as to his own concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, we muſt confeſs, that your affairs being almoſt in a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate condition, becauſe your ſubtilty could not overpoiſe thoſe Forces, which were a falling upon you from all ſides; <hi>How was it poſſible for us to hope to preſerve our ſelves?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lay aſide, I beſeech you, that paſſion which hath poſſeſſed you; let not the ſucceſs of your Armies, blot out the memory of what is paſt; and permit us to repreſent unto you the evils of a War, whenas not neceſſary: and call to minde thoſe ſtreights and agonies, which cauſed you ſo often <hi>to long for an honourable Peace;</hi> and thoſe vowes which you continually made, that you would not ſuffer your ſelf to be tranſported by the flattering appearances of the good ſucceſs of your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; which reſolves were more then once by you taken; nay, as often as the wrath of God, or rather his goodneſs, endeavoured to bring you to reaſon, through the proſperity of the <hi>Allyes Forces.</hi> And if as yet you cannot attribute any faith to our words, we beſeech you only to reflect on the <hi>Condition of Prince</hi> Regotsky; <hi>conſider him, and be more herein jointly with us: Remember, what this good Prince, who hath don<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſo much for you, is come to, and in what a manner you have relieved him;</hi> although he be happier then we, by reaſon that you pitty him, for having loſt himſelf for your ſakes; <hi>whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>as you reproach the Elector, becauſe he would not periſh with you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But not to enlarge upon theſe Afflictions, the remembrance whereof cannot chooſe but be very ſenſible to thoſe who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any ſparkles of humanity and tenderneſs; let us ſet what you mean, by your endeavouring to perſwade us, <hi>That we might have avoided the encountring of all theſe misfortunes, in caſe we would have done that which</hi> (according to your own
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:133421:22"/>advice) <hi>was neceſſary and eaſie.</hi> We ingeniouſly confeſs, that we cannot perceive your meaning; but we very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, to have ſeen you ſo ſurpriſed, and aſtoniſhed in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, <hi>That you believed, you both bought, and could perſwade his Electoral Highneſſe, that there was a neceſſity he ſhould joyn his Forces unto yours, and ſo to periſh joyntly with you. The one (indeed) was very neceſſary for your ſervice alone, and the other ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eaſie, both to yours and ours.</hi> You would have us to reject the juſt complaint of our good Subjects; to deſpiſe the cruell threatnings of our enemies, and yet by a more then Stoicall indifferency, we ſhould have ſat croſs-armed, and looked upon the ſeveral devaſtations of our Provinces.</p>
               <p>And to the end, that there might be nothing wanting to that inviolable friendſhip which you retained for us, your Ambaſſadours ceaſed not mean while to repreſent, <hi>That the Elector would do well to yeild</hi> Pruſſia <hi>to the King, as a Province which could not chooſe but be burdenſome and chargeable to the Prince Elector; and that we ſhould do well to put our Ports into his hands.</hi> Without doubt, becauſe we ſhould not reap the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, to ſee them periſh in our own; and that we might at leaſt receive the ſatisfaction, to ſee them taken from the <hi>Swedes,</hi> who doubtleſs would be ſo good unto us, as to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence us for the ſame, out of thoſe Conqueſts they ſhould make in</hi> Poland, <hi>and</hi> Sileſia; <hi>or it may be, to induce us, to give them that in a generous way, which they had a mind one day to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us.</hi> They would have ingaged us to have entred <hi>Sileſia</hi> with our Army, and to have made up our ſhare, by the <hi>ruine of the Empire of</hi> Germany; without their reflecting on the Obligation which the Elector oweth unto the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruor, and the aſſurances which the King himſelf had ſo often given, That he would never moleſt or trouble the repoſe thereof. They were ſo ill adviſed, as to counſell us to ſet upon others Eſtates, at ſuch a time, when we could not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Polanders</hi> from falling into our own; nor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Capitall City of their Kingdom, and the chief Peace of our Conqueſts: And all your policy conſiſted, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to blow into our cars, that there was a neceſſity to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and delay the Treaties, to gain time, and to make us
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:133421:23"/>hope that the King would ſpeedily return again into <hi>Pruſſia.</hi> And you ſo well compaſſed your deſignes thereby, as that whereas we both could have, and ought to have made uſe of the occaſion, and have concluded our Treaty immediately, we only finiſhed it at the end of four Moneths; neither did we ſign the Treaty with <hi>Poland,</hi> ſave after we diſcovered that your King did but dally with us, whileſt our condition grew every day worſe and worſe; and that the <hi>Polanders</hi> took advantages at the ſmall appearance of relief, which we could promiſe our ſelves from the King of <hi>Sweden:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to our thinkings, we proceeded ſo warily, as you your ſelves cannot condemn it. Inſomuch, as though you will hardly avouch it, ſave in an indirect manner: However, we hope that one day you will come to your ſelves again, and that you will be more rational.</p>
               <p>We full well know, that it is not your cuſtom to harbour any complaiſance for your Friends: Inſomuch, as that by your boaſting, <hi>to have permitted the Elector to enter into a Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation for a Newtrality,</hi> you confeſs you have done more, then you believed you were bound to do; becauſe you do in ſome manner acknowledge, that amidſt our humane actions, there happens ſome conjunctures which oblige us to give way unto neceſſity. But although we ſpeak with ſo much advantage of you, we do not intend to leſſen the glory which we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count due to your King, who being deſirous to give a finall proof of his friendſhip unto his <hi>Electoral Highneſſe,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that he alone was expoſed to the diſcretion of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, contrary to the Treaty between them; <hi>did not permit him</hi> (for he could not have done leſs to one of his Subjects) <hi>but counſelled him as his Friend and Kinſman, to make a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Newtrality with</hi> Poland; we are not a little obliged to you however, for what you ſay thereon, ſince we could hardly perſwade our ſelves you had been capable to averre, That we did well to make a Treaty of Newtrality, whileſt you reject that Treaty, by which we quit your alliance; and to acknowledge the neceſſity of the one, whileſt you abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely condemn the other.</p>
               <p>We beſeech you <hi>(Gentlemen)</hi> to conſider, that your
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:133421:23"/>cenſure is either too ſevere, or rather unjuſt: Whereas ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging the neceſſity, you refuſe to admit the Lawes of Tyranny; Nature it ſelf teacheth, that in ſome things, you muſt of neceſſity go from one extreamity to another. A man cannot ſtop himſelf, being on a Precipice; and a River that overflowes, cannot be ſtopped by one ſole ditch: The revolutions of great things, cannot be ſmall; and thoſe things which are well interwoven, cannot be unſowed; you muſt either tear them, or cut them aſunder. We could not remain allyed with you, and ſeek the Friendſhip of the <hi>Poles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For you your ſelves (Swediſh Sirs) alledge, <hi>That one muſt be either a Friend, or declared Enemy, to a Prince who hath an Army on foot.</hi> And for all this, you would have us remain Neutrall with the <hi>Poles;</hi> that is to ſay, you would have us become their Enemies, whileſt they are Victorious; and you would have us remain your Friends in your misfortunes. As if it were as eaſie to us, not to bear down whatſoever we ſhould meet withall in our fall, after you ſhall have ingaged and forced us on the Precipice, as it hath been eaſie for us to hinder our ſelves from falling. Undeceive therefore your ſelves, and learn of us, <hi>That never a Victorious party granted a Newtrality to a declared Enemy:</hi> And that it was by a ſecret diſpoſall, and decree of God, we were forced to take part with the <hi>Poles;</hi> and that otherwaies your pretended Newtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity could not ſave us.</p>
               <p>And hereon it is, that you ſo mainly fly out, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to cry down our proceedings, with a great deal of ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity; and wherein the <hi>Polanders</hi> themſelves, have been farre more reaſonable then you, who had exclaimed againſt us, before we ever had aſſiſted the Enemy in the leaſt: And although it may ſeem, we have preferred warre before Peace, yet however we not any waies alter the reſolution which we have taken, inceſſantly to labour for accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and farre from repenting our ſelves of that agreement which we have made with the <hi>Polanders,</hi> we are fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that it is the only meanes to preſerve each other, and to beget an honourable and reaſonable Peace between the two Crownes.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:133421:24"/>
               <p>Moreover, thoſe Injuries and Aſperſions which you caſt upon us, do ſo much the leſs concern us, as by them you mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, That you only have regard to your own Intereſts; and that all thoſe, who will go about to make themſelves ſure of the Swediſh friendſhip, muſt reſolve to labour in the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Dominion, even at the expences of their Goods and Liberties.</p>
               <p>We are aſhamed to repreſent unto you, in a large diſcourſe, all thoſe things which you know we have done for you; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are we diſpoſed to reproach you with the proofes of the friendſhip and good will which our Prince hath teſtified unto you in ſuch a manner, as well as thoſe Obligations you are indebted to him for what he did at the execution of the firſt Treaty; you your ſelves do know it full well, and your Letters which do ſo often promiſe an external acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereon to his Electorall Highneſs, will alwaies teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the ſame unto poſterity. It ſufficeth us, <hi>That the Plaines of</hi> Warſawe, <hi>that all</hi> Maſſow, <hi>and</hi> Poland <hi>to boot, doth pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it.</hi> Nor can your warlike Exploits be mentioned, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpecifying of our ſhares at the ſame time; and that it is very well known, <hi>It was our Money, and our Forces, which ſupported your drooping Fortune.</hi> And which is more then all this, <hi>By un unheard of prodigality, we have ſet you up again, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with the perill of our life, and the forfeiture of our reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However, we do not deny, that we ever undertook a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Warre, ſave with a reſolution to let ſlip no occaſions to make Peace, and to re-eſtabliſh the publique tranquility; to which end, we often ſtopped your extravagancies, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of an accommodation, which we did not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, but alſo urged them moſt preſſingly, even in the midſt of our Victories. For we repreſented unto our ſelves warre with all its ſequell of evils; we conceived that the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of our Armes were to be made uſe of, to ſmother the ſaid fire, as alſo to diſperſe the very aſhes of it. And we deemed, <hi>That it was only the part of Thieves and Murderers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> wage Warre, for the love of Wirre it ſelf.</hi> And that it is a ſad diſaſter, to declare againſt God, and againſt all men, by boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:133421:24"/>and glorying, in the ſacrifyſing of the life, the honour, and the ſouls of an infinite number of Chriſtians, to our am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition. True it is, that your King hath often given ear to theſe and the like overtures, and hath ever deſired the <hi>Elector to make up a Peace upon tollerable Conditions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, if he, who was the cauſe of the warre, both would, and could do it; Why do you <hi>(Gentlemen)</hi> find fault that we have done it? We, who had only taken up Armes in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half? Why would you not have us rid our ſelves of a warre which we did not begin? And why will you not have us make ſuch a Peace, which makes us hope to obtain that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which we are engaged, through our Intereſt to procure and eſtabliſh a Peace betwixt two Kings who are our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? This very conſideration, and this very neceſſity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained us to ſide with the <hi>Polanders,</hi> purpoſely to procure a Peace for you, and to reſtore quietneſs to the others.</p>
               <p>VVherefore we beſeech you to ſpare us, and not to abuſe and ſlander our Prince, who is the beſt of your Friends. VVe have ſided with the <hi>Polanders,</hi> that's true, but it was through conſtraint; nor can the Treaty which we have made, be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial unto you, in caſe you be capable of reaſon; and therefore you cannot reproach us, for having Treated an alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance at <hi>Bromberg;</hi> the conditions whereof cannot diſpleaſe you at all; unleſs that you are diſpleaſed to ſee thereby, that we have undertaken to re-eſtabliſh Peace and quietneſs in our Territories. VVe proteſt before God, that we have no other intention; and we ought to believe, That an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Peace would not be undiſpleaſing unto you. And this hope, was chiefly confirmed unto us by the French Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours, who did not only aſſure all the world of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination you bore to Peace, but h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath alſo declared in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, That you were ready to reſtore <hi>Pruſſia</hi> for a ſumme of Money: wherein alſo, we proffered our aſiſtance from the very time we were at <hi>Bromberg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For being obliged to give you notice, that we were entred upon an alliance with <hi>Poland,</hi> we could not any more give you entrance into our Ports, nor paſſage through our Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories; to which we were glad to adde, <hi>That</hi> Poland <hi>only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:133421:25"/>a Peace:</hi> That according to all appearance, the agreement might be made in few daies; and that if it pleaſed the King, to make known his Intentions to the Elector, and to Intruſt him with the Conditions, there ſhould be no Treaty capable to engage him to take up Arms againſt him, in caſe the King would ſubmit to any thing that was reaſon: The Count of <hi>Slippenbach,</hi> your own Ambaſſadour, could not chooſe but praiſe his <hi>Electoral Highneſs</hi> good Intentions, and approved of the Treaty which was made with <hi>Poland;</hi> of which he ſaid, His King had no great reaſon to complain: and himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, That thoſe things might be excepted without offence, which you could not with equity have hoped to have poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one day.</p>
               <p>VVherefore you are the more unjuſt, and not willing to remember all thoſe paſſages, you change your opinion, and likewiſe altring your Tenents. After ſeveral ſad reproaches, you have the impudence to alledge, <hi>That his Electoral High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, hath promiſed to ſuccour the</hi> Polanders <hi>in the Empire.</hi> But this you ſhall never be able to prove; The Treaty ſpeakes quite contrary. And had you but the leaſt friendſhip for the Elector, and for the Truth it ſelf, you will eaſily perceive, <hi>That the ſole refuſall which he made, to give paſſage to the Poliſh Troops through</hi> Pomerania <hi>into</hi> Holſtein, <hi>was that which ſaved you.</hi> True it is, that the ſaid <hi>Polanders</hi> made one irruption into the Swediſh <hi>Pomerania:</hi> but it is alſo true, that this hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned whileſt the Elector was with his Army in <hi>Pruſſia;</hi> and the loſs which we ſuſtained thereby, doth ſufficiently denote our innocence.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee (Gentlemen) how you thrive by your Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſations; for all your following diſcourſe, even to the end, is in the like ſtyle. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndeed, you talk much, <hi>of the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence we ſhould have held with the King of</hi> Denmark, <hi>and what a deſign we had to joyn our Forces to Warre upon you:</hi> But this you muſt prove: You do accuſe, without proofes, and do ſlander without fear of being puniſhed. In the conjuncture of affairs, at the time, we were threatned, we were ſought unto; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes were fomented againſt us, and proffers were made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, as unto a Prince, who had not as yet declared himſelf:
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:133421:25"/>and to my thinking, that we had the civility to hearken to thoſe Propoſals, it cannot be miſinterpreted, ſince it is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our power not to hear, or not to ſuffer another to ſpeak.</p>
               <p>Why would you not have it left to the Electors choice, to give ear to thoſe Propoſitions which were made? to anſwer them? and to treat upon them ſince you were not prejudiced, neither his Electorall Highneſs engaged thereby? We cannot beleeve that your King intends to debarre <hi>a free Prince</hi> from his liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, eſpecially ſuch a one as doth not acknowledg him in the leaſt. But becauſe we cannot imagin, that a <hi>Prince</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth generoſity ſhould poſſibly be capable to harbour ſuch a conceit; we ſhall reſt ſatisfied by urging you to prove, not, that we never began, but that we ever ended thoſe Negotia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: not, that we have not only begun, but alſo that we have concluded, ſigned, and ratified the ſaid Treaties; as then we ſhall willingly beleeve your allegations, although otherwiſe there is but little faith to be given to you.</p>
               <p>That which you alledg concerning the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> is moſt abominably falſe: But patience; we can diſpell theſe Illuſions as well as the others: All men know at what a val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue the ſaid Houſe is in <hi>Germany;</hi> wherefore we ſhall not need to anſwer your allegation, which we account meerly as a thing which partly is not at all, or if there be any thing of it, it is ſo remote from truth, as that we ſhall only ſay, <hi>Had you not threatned us, we had not needed to have troubled our ſelves with alliances;</hi> and that we beleeve, the Elector might have made an alliance with as great a Prince of <hi>Germany,</hi> without asking you leave; unleſs you already perſwade your ſelves to be Maſters of the liberties of all the Princes of the Empire. But we have juſt reaſon to complain, whenas this ſaid alliance, having not paſſed the tearms and limits of a juſt and lawfull defence; you take occaſion thereby to cry us down, as if we had conſpired againſt you; becauſe you hope to draw this advantake thence, <hi>That your Calumnies, though never ſo falſe, will alwayes leave ſome impreſſions in mens mindes, capable to make us odious:</hi> all the world knows, we alwayes abhorred Warre, neither did we ever enter into any Negotiation whatſoever,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:133421:26"/>no not with your ſelves, but our ends were for Peace. We endeavoured to make Friends on all ſides, that we might the better compaſs the aforeſaid ends; and we confeſs, that we were not ſorry ſometimes to ſee the great proſperities of the victorious checked by ſmall adverſities, to render them the more capeable of reaſon.</p>
               <p>Nor can we forbear to tell you that you are beſides your wits, when you alledg, <hi>That we ſhared the Eſtates and Province<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of your King, and that we have treated him as a common Enemy.</hi> You may ſay what you pleaſe; but you are ſo farre from proving of it, that to the contrary, we will give whatſoever you pleaſe, <hi>That in caſe you undertake nothing againſt your Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that your Armies enter not into the Empire, that you leave the Prince Elector and his Eſtates in tranquillity,</hi> we will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly never pretend any thing of <hi>Sweden,</hi> nor upon your other Eſtates in <hi>Germany;</hi> but that alſo we ſhall alwayes retain that reſpect and conſideration for the <hi>Kings Perſon,</hi> which we owe to his deſerts, and to the advantage of his birth which he hath had in one of the moſt Illuſtrious Families of all <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny:</hi> wherefore we can hardly reſolve to adde hereunto, That this Alliance, of which you ſo much talk, which hath been negotiated with ſo much circumſpection, and the concluſion whereof hath for a great while together been delayed, even by the conſent of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> purpoſely to debarre you from all evaſions of refuſing the Peace, was not concluded and ratified, till ſuch time as it was known, that you decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your ſelves publikely againſt the Peace; and after they began openly to diſclaim that ſecurity which was promiſed us againſt their threatnings and violences.</p>
               <p>The ſame reaſon hinders us from anſwering thoſe things which you alledg, concerning <hi>ſuccours, leavies, garriſons, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezvous of Armies, ceiſing of Gunpowder,</hi> &amp;c. for we can very wel juſtifie our ſelves by one word, <hi>denying what you ſay, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> have not hindred your leavies; That we demanded no ſuccours againſt you; That we diſturbed not your aſſembling of your Troops.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the other things you reproach us with, they are ſuch indifferent and free voluntary ones, as that we might do by them as we pleaſed our ſelves, without the offring you any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury at all.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:133421:26"/>
               <p>And as concerning your <hi>Gunpowder,</hi> you may thank your ſelves, we had given your King notice thereof long time before; and we had ſo deeply engaged our ſelves to the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> that we would not permit any ammunitions of warre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o paſs, as that we could not break our word, unleſs we were minded to have expoſed our ſelves again to thoſe hoſtilities which we choſe to avoid by the ſaid alliance which we made with them.</p>
               <p>Which being ſo, and that there is not any thing to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied thereunto, it doth of neceſſity hence ariſe, <hi>That we have not committed any act of hoſtility againſt you in the Empire, and that we ſided not with the Polanders ſave upon conſtraint.</hi> Inſomuch as that without all doubt, in caſe you had been as much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined unto Peace, as we alwayes were, it would be an eaſie matter to preſerve it amongſt us, and that on both ſides we might enjoy a profound tranquility, and by a happy ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion leave to our Poſterities the Eſtates which the Almighty hath entruſted under our Government. The very name of <hi>Warre</hi> ought to be terrible; nor truly can it be pleaſing, ſave only unto ſuch ears as bear no reſpect to thoſe things which are above them, nor fear of thoſe which are below them. But we of all men abhor it the more, by how much we cannot endure it amongſt thoſe whoſe proximity of Neighbourhood or the bond of Amity, ought to contain within the ſtreighter limits and tyes of conjunction. Would to God you had har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured the ſame thoughts, and God grant as yet you may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs them: truly it is a part of your duty; and, if ſo be the charming name of Peace, if the continuall prayers of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, if the juſt apprehenſions of ill ſucceſſes of an unjuſt war, and if the ſenſe of the wrath of God, which hath been ſo raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provoked, are not ſufficient to cauſe you to change your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions; at leaſt you ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſider (if poſſibly you can) That the hopes of an inconſiderable advantage, ought not to have ſo great an aſcendent upon you, as meerly in a frolick and in an humour, to caſt a faithfull Friend, into an irreco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verable enmity.</p>
               <p>You full well know, we have <hi>ſworne</hi> to the Alliance which we have made with <hi>Poland:</hi> and ſince you enforced us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:133421:27"/>it was a part of your prudence to have endeavoured the regaining of a Friend, who had not as yet offended you; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of declaring warre againſt him, and reducing him to the laſt extremity: unleſs it turns more to your advantage <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have conſtrained him to declare himſelf againſt you. Now if there be any fault in this which we have done, ſurely you that have enforced us thereunto cannot ſcape innocent.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Intereſts of Religion,</hi> which are alledged, are very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable; 'tis true, but the means to preſerve them were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded unto you, as well as the others; ſince the <hi>Polanders</hi> proffered to have a care thereof, and to remedy all thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars which might have induced you to wage warre; and all this with the more certainty as to Religion, in that the conſcience and the Religion of the Elector found their ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Soveraignty of <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> which the King had granted unto him. But we muſt likewiſe confeſs, That you did not greatly heed Religion, <hi>whether or no you judg wiſely and piouſly, that ſhe may be perſwaded, but not commanded: that it is not war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, but a godly life; not force or violence, but ſufferings to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes which eſtabliſh it:</hi> or whether you really know, that there is no place in the world where the pretence of Religion is of leſs effect in martiall affairs, as in <hi>Poland.</hi> For it is moſt true, and we know it by experience, that the warre hath moſt of all ſhaken the ſtate of our Religion; and whereas in times of peace we enjoyed an entire liberty of conſcience through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all <hi>Poland,</hi> the warres were no ſooner begun there again, but in hatred unto your forces, they perſecuted thoſe who made profeſſion of the Proteſtant Religion; whereas Peace would have preſerved the ſame, and alſo by a Treaty you might have had great advantages granted for the furtherance of the ſame.</p>
               <p>But truly, this is not th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ing which we can expect from you; for <hi>how can thoſe be zealous as to concernments of Religion, who are manifeſtly unjuſt? by demanding and poſſeſsing of Pruſsia!</hi> who violate all the Laws of Friendſhip, to become Maſters of the <hi>Baltick Sea?</hi> We have ſeen you ſtirre Heaven and earth, toſſe all things topſiturvy, make no diſtinction betwixt Friends or Enemies, party or party, to compaſs your deſigns,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:133421:27"/>which you have laid to joyn all theſe ſpatious and great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces to your Crown.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is an effect and mark of your Religion,</hi> but whereof till now we had not learnt the rules, when you ſay (for you do not at all diſguize it) <hi>that Kings are the Maſters of all.</hi> It is a pretious and pious Notion to ſay, That the <hi>Polanders</hi> are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in conſcience to defend Chriſtendome from the invaſions of ſo many Enemies and barbarous Nations, whileſt your poverty permits you to be pious, and puts you in a moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed condition, if your ill fortune ſhut you up at home, where you will alwaies reap this comfort, by the aſſurance you have, that you may alwayes unpuniſhed aſſault others, without your fearing of being aſſaulted by others in your own homes. In caſe your King be reſolved to continue the warres, which we hardly beleeve, he would not be a little troubled to beget the ſame minde in all thoſe of his party. <hi>It would prove a new unheard of kinde of Juſtice, to prefer warre before peace;</hi> Pruſſia <hi>before the intereſts of the whole world; and your particular Laws to the Almighties.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In regard whereof, the Prince Elector being ſenſibly touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all theſe diſorders, and ſeeing that the ſtate of affairs required him to take a ſtrong reſolution either to prevent and remedy them, or to periſh: he would eſſay whether his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample might prove capable to bring you back unto reaſon; or at leaſt in caſe our ſinnes would not permit us to hope that, to try whether all honeſt men might not be perſwaded, <hi>That it was not his fault the Peace was not made, and that all the North at this preſent doth not enjoy a profound Tranquillity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince this hath not ſucceeded, by reaſon that your King, not being ſatisfied with his too unadviſed rejecting our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſie, endeavours moreover to caſt a blame upon us, which he knoweth cannot be excuſed on his part: you will therefore not take it ill (Gentlemen) that we both remit you, and our ſelves, unto the judgement of the whole world, as to what is paſt, that ſo they may immediately decide this firſt que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether or no, in the preſent conjuncture of affairs, the Elector can be blamed, for having ſent Ambaſſadours to the King?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:133421:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether or no his Majeſty hath done well, to ſend us back again without hearing of us?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whether it may not be ſaid, That the King by refuſing to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg us, otherwaies then in the quality of Ambaſſadours from Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, hath not declared Warre againſt the Electorall Highneſs? and whether, by refuſing of the Peace, he hath not infringed the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We are willing to remit our ſelves hereon, unto your own ſelves (Gentlemen,) and we have ſo good an opinion of your prudence, and of your juſtice, as that we perſwade our ſelves, your belief is the ſame with ours, <hi>That the Motions which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the Elector to depute this Embaſſie, are good and Religious, and that the Parties which were employed therein, did behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like Perſons of Honour;</hi> and therefore we conceive we ought not to inſiſt any further thereon. For ſince we had no other deſign, ſave to preſerve that Friendſhip which we had contracted with you, and to procure a juſt and honourable Peace between the two Crowns, to your advantage, to the content of all our Friends and Allyes, and for the repoſe and peace of our conſciences; <hi>me thinks, we might have gone directly to the King, although we had been your declared Enemies; we might have done it, I ſay, becauſe you had approved of it:</hi> for I pray, what other means have you, ſpeedily to remedy thoſe diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which afflict us? You are all Learned men, and you know that one Aſſociate may act for the other; and moreover it may eaſily be perceived, that our Prince did ſend this Embaſſie unto you with a very good intention; not as an Enemy, but as a Friend; not with your thoughts, but with his own. Do but conſider I pray, with how much moderation we have taken notice of you; that even ſince the peace of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and ſince it was known that this Embaſſie was reſolved on, neither your King, nor his Miniſters, have not in the leaſt denied thoſe obligations you owe unto us. For you approved of all, you did not condemn that which we had done with <hi>Poland,</hi> with the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and with <hi>Denmark,</hi> you found no fault therewith; and you continued to make us hope, that notwithſtanding all that was paſt, we ſhould live in a good underſtanding together: you ſought to us for our
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:133421:28"/>friendſhip, and you publikely praiſed the prudence and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of his Electorall Highneſs.</p>
               <p>The King himſelf, writing with his own hand to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, indate the 10th of <hi>April,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That it concerned the Elector to make the Peace with</hi> Poland; <hi>and that therefore his Majeſty could not expect from his Electorall Highneſs (as from a moſt faithfull Friend) ſave all kind of good offices, and ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices whereof he might make uſe, to deliver himſelf from ſo many Enemies as had declared themſelves againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Count of <hi>Slippenbach</hi> having deſired the Conference at <hi>Prenſlou,</hi> after he had produced by the Kings Order, thoſe pretended Treaties of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and after ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall diſcuſſings on all ſides, did not only preſs this Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; but alſo having received thoſe new Orders which the King had ſent him from <hi>Gottemburg;</hi> he proteſted both by word of mouth, and by writing, that there could not be any thing done which would be more acceptable to the King.</p>
               <p>The Lord <hi>Wolsberg,</hi> your Reſident in our Court, continued his Offices hereon with ſo much urgency, as that we ſhall not need to ſpecifie Mr. <hi>Tophſon</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Blondel</hi>'s inſtances which they added, on the behalf of the King of <hi>France,</hi> and of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> nor the ſeverall Embaſſies which the Dukes of <hi>Brunſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, Lunenburg,</hi> and the Lantſgrave of <hi>Heſs,</hi> have ſent unto us, as upon the ſame account: Inſomuch as that it needs not to be wondred at, if the Elector, who of himſelf had a great inclination to Peace, at length did yeeld to the counſils of ſo many illuſtrious Perſonages.</p>
               <p>Having therefore left <hi>Berlin,</hi> and having reached your Garriſons, we were there very well received, particularly at <hi>Kiel;</hi> where the Prince of <hi>Sulsbach,</hi> did us more honour then we could have expected: we know not whether the King may have repented himſelf in having been ſo prodigall of his firſt Civilities; which however, we can ſcarce believe from his generoſity, although we have reaſon to apprehend it, by that which followed after: However, we owe very much to the obliging fault which that Prince may have committed, by taking the paines, to come purpoſely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Gottorp,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert us, during the tediouſneſs, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>ings long abſence
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:133421:29"/>might have cauſed: <hi>He not only received us with a great deal of civility,</hi> and aſſured us, <hi>That the King retained a particular af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for the Elector; but he alſo feaſted us at his Houſe, and did us the honour to viſit us in our lodgings.</hi> The Count of <hi>Slippen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bach,</hi> arrived likewiſe much about the ſame time, and uſed us with the ſame reſpects and civilities, on the behalf of the King.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as we heard the King was arrived in <hi>Holſtein,</hi> we went ſpeedily to <hi>Gottorp;</hi> and that we might not fail in the uſual formes, and accuſtomed manners of proceeding, we would not advance to <hi>Flensbourg,</hi> without the Kings expreſs aſſent: For the Prince of <hi>Sulsbach</hi> having advertiſed the King of our arrivall, we had notice, that the King left us to our Liberties, either to expect him at <hi>Gottorp,</hi> or to go to him to <hi>Flensbourg,</hi> whether we went, and found a Houſe appointed for our reception; And we were complemented in our lodgings, however with a kind of coldneſs, after we had communicated our Letters of Credence.</p>
               <p>After which, they began to delay and deferre our audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and finally, <hi>Seeing you could not dive into the particulars of our Commiſſion, nor know what we had to ſay concerning the Peace, and touching the reſtitution of</hi> Pruſſia, <hi>and that there were no more hopes left, to make us renounce thoſe alliances which we had made, to engage us on your ſide, and involve us blindly in a Warre, which you are reſolved to continue and proſecute, to eſtabliſh your Dominion:</hi> You began publickly to witneſs an adverſion againſt us, to reproach us with things which were not, and to <hi>refuſe us audience.</hi> And that there might be nothing wanting to the entire affront, you intended to put upon us; you would have rendred us guilty, and have cauſed us to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear as criminals before your ſelves, and before the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of <hi>Lunenbourg</hi> and <hi>Heſſe; which was not the way to enter into a Conference, but into a Conteſt.</hi> You had prepared your ſelves, not to have payed us with reaſon, but to have charged us with injuries; and inſtead of having diſpoſed things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a reconcilion you did but exaſperate them, purpoſely to bring them to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> open rupture: It was not your intent to make up the breaches in the preſence of thoſe Princes Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:133421:29"/>which are our common Friends, but to render them irrecoverable; to embroyl us with them, and thence to have obtained a plauſible pretence, <hi>to have ſent us away without the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us an audience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Truly we are aſhamed to recount all theſe particulars; you very well know, <hi>that we alwaies proteſted, we were ſo farre from being charged with declarations of Warre, as that we were laden with propoſitions, which could not chooſe but be welcome.</hi> But becauſe we have formerly enlarged upon this point in the Letter which we wrote from <hi>Hamborrow;</hi> we believe we may conclude, that his <hi>Electorall Highneſs intention being good, pious, and glorious;</hi> and the Embaſſie well ordered and conſented unto; doubtleſs, no body will ſtick to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch, <hi>That the King by his ſo evill intreating us, and by not r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding us as he ought to have done, hath violated the peace, and hath too raſhly rejected our amity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For in caſe the King reflected upon the Teaty which the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector made with <hi>Poland;</hi> why did he not regard us as <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours from an Elector of the Empire?</hi> ſince you your ſelves would be otherwiſe conſidered <hi>then Swedes,</hi> and otherwiſe then <hi>Princes of the Empire; and that in Sweden you would be Enemies, but in the Empire friends to the King of Poland?</hi> If he knew the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector was his Enemy, why did he deſire him to ſend his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours? why did he receive them? and why did he treat them civily? and if he received them, <hi>why did he refuſe them audience?</hi> ſo wiſe a King as himſelf, ought either not to have received them, or having received them, ought not to have denied them audience, unleſs he will aſſume that authority to himſelf <hi>to abuſe the Princes of the Empire, by rejecting and driving away the Ambaſſadours,</hi> however we are loath to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſo much of him.</p>
               <p>You alledge it is true, <hi>that the dignity of the Common-wealth permits not an audience to be given to the Ambaſſadours of an Enemy in the Senate.</hi> But how can you believe that the Elector was the Enemy? ſince he laboured in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> towards the procuring of an Agreement, even with your conſents; and that he rather endeavoured Peace then Warre, and how can you convince him of the leaſt hoſtilities in the Empire, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you conceit you build them upon imaginary apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:133421:30"/>or upon the uncertain reports which are ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, againſt which there are other remedies then force and violence; Time would have taught you the one, and the divine providence accompanied by an innocent precauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, would have cured you of the other.</p>
               <p>But ſuppoſe the Elector had declared himſelf againſt you that could not juſtifie you neither; For the example of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Pagans would have taught you, <hi>that there is nothing ought to hinder the hearing of an Ambaſſadour,</hi> no not from declared Enemies: were it but to let the world ſee, <hi>that you only wage Warre to obtaine Peace.</hi> The firſt Chriſtians would have made a ſcruple of conſcience to have done otherwiſe; But to deſire a Prince to ſend his Ambaſſadours, to make much of them, to receive them at Court, and afterwards to ſend them away again, refuſing them audience; is a thing not only un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of, but againſt all piety, againſt the publick faith, and againſt the Law of Nations.</p>
               <p>We marvell that you endeavour to excuſe this reproach by the Maxime, <hi>That the Law of Nations and former cuſtomes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the receiving of Ambaſſadours, according unto the dignity of the Prince which ſends them; and in relation unto the nature of the buiſneſs whereon they are to Treat;</hi> all which is juſt as much as nothing; For that is only to be underſtood, as to the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and exterior honours which are uſually done to the perſons of Ambaſſadours; which is not our diſpute: we are agreed as to the ceremonies; inſomuch as that if you would deliberate, whether you ſhould receive the Embaſſie or no, whether the Elector ſhould be conſidered as a declared Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or as a ſuſpected Prince, who was ready to Arme againſt you; that you might have done at leaſt, if you could have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us to have been ſuch, before your having approved of our Embaſſie, by your receiving of us. We do not deny, but that ſometimes Ambaſſadours may be refuſed to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but to deny thoſe Ambaſſadours audience, who have been received, this we deny expreſly; and do judg it the more extravagant, ſince in things of ſo high an importance, Sovereigns cannot proceed with too much circumſpection.</p>
               <p>We likewiſe ſay, that it is an unheard of thing, to go about
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:133421:30"/>to oblige an Ambaſſadour, who hath been received, and acknowledged as ſuch, to declare the ſubject of his Embaſſie, and his ſecret Inſtructions, before he hath ſpoken with the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty unto whom he is ſent; and likewiſe to endeavour to force him to undergo a kinde of Interrogatory before Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, <hi>this is very impertinent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All men know that the Character of an Ambaſſadour, is moſt holy and inviolable between Princes and Soveraignes, and that from all ages, and amongſt all people, they have been received with honour and reſpect, and that their perſons are held in the more veneration, by reaſon they repreſent thoſe Kings and Princes by whom they are ſent. Now whether this be performed or no, by thoſe manner of proceedings which you uſe, we deſire you your ſelves (Gentlemen) to judge.</p>
               <p>Truly we believe that there is not one amongſt you, who would not be offended; if a friend having appointed you an houre to come and viſit him, ſhould let you ſtay in the Hall, and ſhould ſend to know of you by a Foot-boy or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his doneſtick Servants, that thing which you would not diſcloſe ſave unto himſelf; But there is great deale of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between Princes and particuler Perſons: wherefore we beſeech you to conſider, whether the moſt barborous Nations in the world would not be laughed at, ſhould they undertake to examine thoſe Ambaſſadours which are ſent unto them, and require of them the ſubject of their Embaſſie; and conſequently whether this kind of proceeding be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, and inſuſportable, eſpecially among ſuch as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs civillity; and whether it be a thing to be endured, that the ſecret which an Ambaſſadour hath expreſs Order to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate to none ſave the Prince unto whom he is ſent, ſhould be extorted from him.</p>
               <p>We ſhould have derogated from that Character where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall our Prince had honoured us, had we been ſo ill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed, as not to have made a diſtinction betwixt the Prince and his Miniſters: Truely Gentlemen, you ſhall hardly be able to perſwade it us; and therefore we beſeech you not to build too much upon the Maxime which you ſo often uſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:133421:31"/>and which makes you ſwerve ſo farre from the mark, <hi>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the dignity of the Commonwealth permits not to hear Enemy Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours in the Senate.</hi> This is no generall rule, nor ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you make uſe of that which was heretofore ſaid only up on the accounts of thoſe who came as Spies (and who would be heard without having asked audience) againſt us; who came upon the publick Faith, who were invited received, and honoured as Friends, and therefore ought not, nor could be gainſaid, nor put by, unleſs you did it purpoſely to offend us, wilfully to faile in the point of civillity, and mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cruelly to outrage us.</p>
               <p>But we have ſaid too much hereon, the thing being ſo clear and manifeſt; <hi>The Lacedemonians, the Florentines, the Duk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Nevers, and the Lord of Langey,</hi> have by their example ſhewn us what is to be done on the like occaſions; to wit, <hi>rather to withdraw then to be affronted.</hi> Wherefore we ſhall only adde one word, that at the ſame time you treated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo ill, your Reſident who was with the Electors perſon a <hi>Berlin,</hi> was there lodged and defrayed, was admitted to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience as often as he pleaſed to demand the ſame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all the other civilities which could be conferred upon a publick perſon.</p>
               <p>We confeſſe we could not imagine what their deſigne ſhould be, by theſe your two different manner of actings, and we had rather remit our ſelves thereon unto others, then to become too importunate, by an overcurious ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereinto; We deſire not to penetrate into your reaſons, and we will leave it to the diſcretion and liberty of others to give your proceedings the blame or praiſe they may deſerve. But our Prince Elector, who doth nothing but what he would have all the world know; troubles himſelf not at all hereat; or in caſe he had remained there to hinder his Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Highneſs from the declaring of himſelf; our Prince who only aſpires after Peace, deſired nothing ſo much as that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven during the midſt of the Wars.</p>
               <p>We may eaſily believe, that you did it purpoſely to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain and amuſe us, till ſuch time as the affairs of <hi>Denmark</hi> being regulated, the King might have proceeded in another
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:133421:31"/>manner with us. <hi>But our generous Prince</hi> vallues this not a ſtraw, for having not at all offended the King, he needed not to apprehend any thing upon that account neither.</p>
               <p>And if it be not in regard of what is before ſaid, at leaſt be pleaſed to tell us, why did the Lord <hi>Wolfsberg</hi> continue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine by your orders in our Court, and to be admitted to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience at all times, whilſt you refuſed it unto us at yours? Why do you go about to make the world believe, that the Elector hath declared himſelf againſt you, <hi>by treating with Poland,</hi> ſince even after the ſaid Treaty, you have had your Miniſters near to the Elector, and have lived in good amity with us? Our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence will not ſuffer us to ſuſpect the faith of ſo great a King.</p>
               <p>But if we be not deceived in the good opinion we had har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured of him, the ill treatment which we have newly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, will not alarm his Electorall Highneſs, but only ſerve to confirme thoſe advices, which have been given us from all ſides; that it is not from this day you have a minde to quarrell us. That you have long ſince harboured that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign which you do now diſcloſe, and that the ſpoiles of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke</hi> will help you to bring forth that which you have been a hammering and hatching ever ſince the beginning of the War. That all your proteſtations of friendſhip, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments, have been but ſo many complements and flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings which your refined wits and ſhallow braines make uſe of to hide their unlimitted ambition by, untill ſuch time as you ſhall be in a capacity to manifeſt it, without ſhame or feare; as it is uſuall to thoſe who ſeek glory otherwiſe then through the footſteps of virtue; to endeavour to render thoſe guilty, whoſe Eſtates they could not poſſibly aſſaile, unleſs they made them profeſt Enemies.</p>
               <p>You know how often you have ſpoken to us concerning <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> the <hi>Pillauw,</hi> and <hi>Pomerania;</hi> you know how great a trouble it was to you to diſguiſe and cloake your inſatiable covetuouſneſs, even during our greateſt friendſhip, as well as the troubles and cares which you have cauſed his Electorall Highneſs by your unjuſt and violent demands.</p>
               <p>After all which, we cannot doubt but you muſt judg (Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen) that by your treating of us as you have done, you
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:133421:32"/>have not done any good either for your ſelves, or for us; and that your King had done more prudently for the common good of affairs; <hi>If after his inviting of us, receiving and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us as friends, he had not turned us off, as Criminals, and ſent us back as Enemies.</hi> You may eaſily judge, in caſe you have the leaſt inclination for Peace; that we ought to have been heard, although you had taken us for common declared Enemies, and that ſince we were not ſo as yet, you ought thereby to have teſtified, that you had ſome reſpect at leaſt to our friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. <hi>By giving audience to the Ambaſſadors of an Elector, you would have manifeſted that you had not any deſigne againſt the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; and by admitting the Prince of Brandenburgs Ambaſſadours, that you had not yet ſtifled the reſentments of an Allye by him, that you had not renounced the duties of Neighbourhood, and that you were ſtill mindefull of what he hath done for you ſome years ſince.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince it ſeems it was not conſiſtent with your pleaſure; The Elector findes himſelf forced to ſay, that he is ſorry to meet with ſo great an obſtinacy, whether it proceeds from an animoſity, from a neglect, or by reaſon of the paſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous ſucceſſes of your forces, and the flattering (though be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiling) hopes which you have thence received.</p>
               <p>This his Electorall Highneſs hath commanded us to ſend you back, in anſwer to your troubleſome and uncivill Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which you wrote unto us from <hi>Flensburg;</hi> and with ſo much the more quietneſs of mind, as he hopes to be able to rectifie yours; proteſting, that he is ſo little moved at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice of your proceedings, as that he deſpiſeth all whatſoever you ſhall be able to undertake againſt the confidence which he repoſeth in the juſtice of his Cauſe, and to the prejudice of the repoſe of his conſcience.</p>
               <p>But to the end you may know his true intentions, he doth declare unto you; that having only taken up Armes with a regret, or againſt his will, and that having ſided with your Party, only when your violence, and the very laſt neceſſity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced him to joyn with you; His reſolution is, moſt punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and religiouſly to performe the promiſe he hath made to his Allies, <hi>and to imploy without any reſervation at all, whatſoever God hath given him, in the procuring of the preſervation of the Peace of the Empire.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:133421:32"/>
               <p>That he wiſheth you all proſperity in thoſe things which you ſhall undertake with juſtice; inſomuch, as that in caſe your King can reſolve to come to a Peace, the Elector will la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourtherein with all his might, and will even give way, that it may be compaſſed in a manner at his charges.</p>
               <p>But and if the King will not hearken to an accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, his Electorall Highneſs doth proteſt, that he will make uſe of all the meanes which God, nature, the juſtice of his Cauſe, and the bublick faith will permit him to employ, for to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to withſtand and repell the violence which ſhall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Signed thus, Gentlemen,</salute> 
                  <signed>Your humble Servants, <hi>O.</hi> Barron of <hi>Suerin, D. Weiman,</hi>
                  </signed>
                  <dateline>Dated from <hi>Collen</hi> on the <hi>Spreè,</hi> 
                     <date>the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1658.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
